<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning Christ his incarnation, and exinanition. As also, concerning the principles of Christianity: by way of introduction. / By Meric Casaubon. D.D.</title>
            <author>Casaubon, Meric, 1599-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 182 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81228</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C803</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E354_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201090</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861655</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861655</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113795</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81228)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113795)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 57:E354[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning Christ his incarnation, and exinanition. As also, concerning the principles of Christianity: by way of introduction. / By Meric Casaubon. D.D.</title>
                  <author>Casaubon, Meric, 1599-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 92 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.F. for R. Mynne, and are to be sold at his shop at the sign of Saint Paul in Little Britain.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7bre [i.e. September] 11th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Incarnation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113795:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113795:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Diſcourſe CONCERNING CHRIST HIS INCARNATION, AND EXINANITION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo, concerning</hi> THE PRINCIPLES OF <hi>CHRISTIANITY: By way of Introduction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By MERIC CASAVBON. D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. F.</hi> for <hi>R. Mynne,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Sign of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in <hi>Little Britain.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:113795:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113795:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Ourteous Reader, what is here offered unto thee under the title of a <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> is the ſubſtance of ſome Sermons preached upon this ſolemn ſacred argument ſome years agoe, where my dwelling and calling then was. The firſt part, which I call the <hi>Introduction,</hi> is, for the moſt part of it, newly added. Why now added, or thought neceſſary, will eaſily be underſtood by them that know (as who knows it not?) what oppoſition the moſt fundamentall points of our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on have met with of late, both at home and abroad. In the reſt, there is more alteration of the form, then addition of matter and ſubſtance. The <hi>Incarnation</hi> of Chriſt is a ſubject which no true Chriſtian can think unſeaſonable at any time. I confeſſe, as it is neceſſary, ſo is it an argument of that ſublimity, as would not be handled by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry body, <hi>illotis manibus.</hi> I had not adventured upon this publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this form, had I not had good encouragement from ſome, whoſe judgement I thought I might truſt to, that it might do good. To that end it is here preſented unto thee: and if thou ſhalt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to thy ſelf that end onely in the reading, there will be the more hopes of the ſucceſſe. Farewell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:113795:3"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>Martinus Lutherus in <hi>Enchiridio Piarum Precationum</hi> De tribus Symbolis, &amp;c.</bibl> IPſà recomperi, &amp; in omnibus Hiſtoriis univerſi Chriſtianiſmi hoc animadverti, quod quicunque principalem illum Chriſtianae fidei Articulum de IESV CHRISTO, verè &amp; incorruptè tum crediderunt tum docuerunt, hi poſteà in vera Chriſtianâ fide tutò ac firmiter perſtiterunt; Et licet ſuos quoſdam errores &amp; ſua peccata habuerint, ſunt illi tamen ad extremum ſervati.</q>
            <p>The ſame in Engliſh.</p>
            <q>WHat by mine own experience, and what by Church Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of all Ages and Nations, I have certainly found and obſerved that as many as truly and ſyncerely have both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved and taught this main Article of the Chriſtian faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning JESUS CHRIST, thoſe have continued ſafe and ſound in the Chriſtian faith; and though perchance for a while they have had their errors and their infirmities, yet at the laſt they have dyed good Chriſtians.</q>
            <pb facs="tcp:113795:3"/>
            <p>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> his opinion and teſtimony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſatisfaction of Chriſt: taken out of his later writings.</p>
            <q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Epheſ. 1.6.</bibl> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hugo Grotius ibi:</hi> Sicut in veteri lege non obtinebatur venia eorum quae in eo ſtatu veniam accipere poterant, niſi cruentâ mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te victimae; ita in novo foedere remittit Deus peccata credentibus in Chriſtum, ideo quia Chriſtus id ſuâ morte cruentâ, quippe ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio perfectiſſimo, Deoque gratiſſimo, pleno obedientiae, demiſſionis, dilectionis &amp; patientiae, ab ipſo nobis impetravit. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, eſt pleniſſima liberatio, à reatuſcilicet. quanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> autem vox <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> tralatione quadam <hi>(quod vulgò excipiunt &amp; objiciunt Sociniani, ſcilicet)</hi> ad liberationem quamvis referri interdum ſolet; in hoc tamen argumento talem intelligi liberationem quae non ſine magno impendio fiat, oſtendit locus <hi>Matth. 20, 28.</hi> ubi Chriſti vita nobis impenſa <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>redemptio,</hi> dicitur.</p>
            </q>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="approbation">
            <pb facs="tcp:113795:4"/>
            <p>I Have peruſed this learned Diſcourſe of Chriſt his <hi>Incarnation</hi> and <hi>Exinanition,</hi> and finding it both ſolid and Orthodox, and alſo adorned with ſuch variety of matter, as may bring to the Reader much profit w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h delight, I allow it to be printed and publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JOHN DOVVNAME.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <list>
               <item>PAg. 3. l. 25. <hi>read</hi> are ready.</item>
               <item>P. 13. l. 4. <hi>according to</hi> in Ital. letter.</item>
               <item>P. 23. l. 7. know not what we.</item>
               <item>P. 40. l. 22, 23. <hi>(as it is written)</hi> in Ital. letter.</item>
               <item>P. 49. l. 30. margin, <hi>Tractatu qui.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>P. 63. l. 3. meanneſſe.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113795:4"/>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>OF THE PRINCIPLES OF DIVINITY; BY WAY OF INTRODUCTION to the enſuing Subject.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL Arts and Sciences are grounded upon ſome common notions and principles, which as they cannot be well proved, (ſome of them at leaſt) ſo they are preſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to carry ſo much evidence with them, as that no rationall man, be he learned or unlear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as ſoon as he heareth them, will ſtick to yeeld aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent unto them: ſo that, be particular propoſitions never ſo ſtrange and incredible of themſelves, or at the firſt hearing; yet if after many turnings and windings they be reduced to ſome common principle, there is no further doubt. Neither is a rationall man bound to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace, for truth, that which is not, either implicitely or explicitely, by neerer or remoter conſequences, reduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuch principles.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113795:5"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theology</hi> or <hi>Divinity,</hi> whether it may properly be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Science or no, it is diſputed amongſt the Learned: I ſhall not diſpute it here, but onely ſay, that <hi>Divinity</hi> alſo hath her common principles; which though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance they bee not of that degree of evidence as the principles of ſome other Sciences are, yet they are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent enough to ſatisfie any rationall man.</p>
               <p>This Doctrine though ſound of it ſelf, and of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent uſe againſt all Heathens, Turks, Infidels, frantick or fanatick Enthuſiaſts, &amp; Anabaptiſts; yet becauſe it is very apt to be miſtaken, and therefore liable to many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, I think it neceſſary, before I come to make that uſe of it, which by way of <hi>Introduction</hi> I aim at in this preſent <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> to ſay ſomewhat of it, to make it more clear &amp; paſſable, then otherwiſe amongſt the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar of men it would be.</p>
               <p>Firſt, then it muſt be obſerved, that to beleeve a thing upon grounds of reaſon, and to comprehend the reaſon, or nature, or poſſibility of that which is beleeved, are things in themſelves far different: which will be made plainer by examples. What reaſonable man can doubt of his ſoul, as of a diſtinct and different nature from the body, being ſo known by the daily effects and operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of it? yet neither is the nature of the ſoul perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comprehenſible to any man: and even thoſe effects and operations of it which are moſt viſible and ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, the moſt underſtanding Phyſitians and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, when they come to ſift them, and to render rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, acknowledge themſelves to be at a ſtand. Nay, the generation of man, that viſible and materiall part of him onely conſidered, (ſetting the ſoul aſide, as of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther origine,) even that hath poſed the wiſeſt and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113795:5"/> wittieſt of men. That the loadſtone hath ſuch and ſuch properties, whereof ſome have been known of old, and ſome have been lately diſcovered, who can queſtion, there being ſuch daily experience of it? But the the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall reaſons of ſuch properties, though much hath been ſaid and written of it of late yeers, yet I think there be but few that will take upon them to know, or to render.</p>
               <p>There is great uſe of this diſtinction in debate and diſputes about the Scripture: which by Ancients is ſaid ſometimes to be very plain and perſpicuous: and ſometimes obſcure and full of incomprehenſible myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: both true, if rightly underſtood. Clear and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous in the delivery of ſuch and ſuch Doctrines, or Articles neceſſary to be known, beleeved, or practiſed to attain ſalvation: but full of obſcurity, or altogether incomprehenſible in their own natures to humane un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. To inſtance in one example: What point of Doctrine can be propoſed to our beleef with more clearneſſe and perſpicuity, then the Reſurrection of the dead? and what more obſcure for the manner and poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of it?</p>
               <p>That nothing therefore is to be beleeved, for which there is not ground in reaſon and humane common ſenſe, is that which we have ſaid, and are really to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in a right ſenſe: but that <hi>Nihil credendum quod ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione capi nequeat; Nothing is to be beleeved, which may not be comprehended by humane reaſon,</hi> (as the Photinians and ſome other Heretiques maintain) is an aſſertion, I know not whether more ridiculous and abſurd in point of reaſon; or more blaſphemous and impious in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Philoſophers are allowed their <hi>occulta qualita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113795:6"/> and Phyſitians, even they who knew little of God o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, did acknowledge <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ewhat above their capacity and the ordinary courſe of nature in things of nature. There be I know that laugh at theſe <hi>occultae qualitates:</hi> and in ſome caſes they may juſtly: neither would I contend about words if another word wil give better content. But as for them who think they can give a reaſon for all which by others is admired as hidden &amp; abſtruſe, ſooner may they bring themſelves into a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpition that they never knew how to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween reaſon and phancy, then perſwade them that are rationall, that no work of nature is above the reach of humane reaſon.</p>
               <p>Our ſecond Obſervation (which follows upon the former, and is a further confirmation of it) ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ambiguity or different acception of this word <hi>faith,</hi> or <hi>beleef. Faith</hi> then we ſay may be taken either in oppoſition to ſight, or ſenſe: or in oppoſition to knowledge and comprehenſion: or thirdly and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to reaſon, in generall. In oppoſition to ſight or ſenſe; ſo things inviſible, whether in their nature ſo, becauſe ſpirituall; or inviſible, becauſe not preſent, but future; are the proper object of faith. In the Epiſtle to the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brews</hi> faith is thus defined; <hi>Faith is the ſubſtance</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>of things hoped for; the evidence</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>of things not ſeen.</hi> In oppoſition to knowledge and comprehenſion; ſo we are ſaid to beleeve thoſe things which we doe not underſtand or comprehend. Laſtly, in oppoſition to reaſon; ſo we are ſaid to beleeve thoſe things for which, or for the beleef of which we have no ground or foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation at all in humane reaſon and ratiocination. Thoſe that ſhall reade the Ancients upon this argument, will
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113795:6"/> finde great uſe of theſe diſtinctions, to reconcile their ſeverall expreſſions, which otherwiſe might ſeem to import <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> contrariety of opinions. For example; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it was commonly objected by ancient Heathens to the Chriſtians of thoſe times, that they grounded all their Doctrine upon meer beleef; that their ſimple faith was all they had to truſt to: Some not ſo aware per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance neither of the ambiguity of the word, nor what advantage Heathens would make of it; made no ſcruple ſimply to avow what was objected unto them: but others again did utterly diſclaim it, complained of the obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction as a groſſe and impudent calumny; appealed to reaſon themſelves for proof of their beleef; and offered themſelves to joyn iſſue with them upon that title. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is that moſt of them in this queſtion did take faith not as oppoſed to reaſon properly; but either to knowledge and comprehenſion; or to ſight and ſenſe. Or if they did uſe the word reaſon in oppoſition to faith, by <hi>reaſon</hi> they did underſtand knowledge and compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion; not as the word was uſed by others. In this ſenſe Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth often oppoſe <hi>Divine authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> to <hi>reaſon;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. de Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Rel.</hi> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas fidem fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitat, &amp; rationi praeparat homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem; ratio ad intellectum per cognitionem perducit: quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam nec au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>horitatem penitùs ratio deſerit, cùm conſideratur cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> credendum ſit, &amp;c.</note> not as though it were againſt humane rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to beleeve thoſe things that are commended unto us by divine revelation or authority, (whereof we ſhall ſay more afterwards) but becauſe moſt of the myſteries of our faith commended unto us by divine authority are ſuch, as are above the reach of humane capacity to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend. Though herein too they did diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Tyrones,</hi> or beginners in Chriſtianity; ſuch as were lately converted to the Chriſtian faith, whom they would have wholly to rely upon authority; and thoſe whom the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.14. ſpeaketh of, <hi>who by reaſon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113795:7"/> of uſe have their ſenſes exerciſed to diſcern both good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill.</hi> Of the uſe of humane reaſon in this kind for the unfolding or underſtanding of particular points (which is a different conſideration from that of the Principles) much hath been written of late by learned <hi>Vedelius,</hi> in a Book of this argument, entituled <hi>Rationale Theologicum;</hi> to which the Reader, if he pleaſe, may have recourſe. I ſhall conclude this Obſervation with the words of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Be ready to give an anſwer to every man that asketh you a reaſon of the hope that is in you, with meekeneſſe and feare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, we would have it obſerved, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this opinion of faith and religion ſo grounded as we have ſaid, we maintain nevertheleſſe that no man can attain to that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that <hi>degree,</hi> or <hi>fulneſſe of faith</hi> required or availeable to ſalvation, but by ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall means, <hi>viz.</hi> by the immediate operation of Gods holy Spirit. To which purpoſe <hi>Origen</hi> in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to <hi>Celſus</hi> the Heathen ſays well:<note place="margin">Orig. contra Celſum l. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>We are taught by the divine Word that what is preached by men (be it of it ſelf ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo true and rationall</hi> (or, <hi>well grounded) cannot ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently penetrate into the ſoul of man, except both ſupernaturall power from God be given to the ſpeaker, and divine grace accompany thoſe things that are ſpoken, &amp;c.</hi> which is by him inferred upon the words of the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4. <hi>And my ſpeech &amp; my preaching was not with inticing words of mans wiſdome, but in demonſtration of the Spirit and of power; that your faith ſhould not ſtand in the wiſedome of men, but in the power of God.</hi> The neceſſity of this infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed faith is acknowledged by Papiſts, as well as by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants: no ſober man that beleeves the Scriptures can make any queſtion of it.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:113795:7"/>
               <p>Fourthly, and laſtly we ſay, though faith be reduci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to principles of reaſon, and in that reſpect become knowledge as well as faith, yet we doe not maintain a neceſſity of this knowledge in all Chriſtians. Without infuſed faith no man is a true Chriſtian; but a man may be a true Chriſtian, though he underſtand not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what grounds of humane reaſon his faith is groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; which innumerable Chriſtians for want either of education, or through naturall indocility, or prevented by death never attain unto.</p>
               <p>If then in Divinity as well as in other Sciences, to proceed with more ſolidity, the conſideration of the firſt principles be ſometimes requiſite; it is in theſe points eſpecially and principally, which of themſelves ſeem moſt contrary to reaſon and common ſenſe: ſuch as this is, <hi>Chriſt his Incarnation.</hi> I know it hath been the opinion of ſome (of Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> by name) that the Incarnation of Chriſt the Son of God, might of it ſelf ſufficiently be demonſtrated and maintained by argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of reaſon. And ſomewhat of that kinde I have ſeen endeavoured by ſome, but never yet any thing which did much ſatisfie me; or whereby I could hope to ſatisfie any other. And I account it a matter of no little danger for men to be too great undertakers in this kind. Wit and ſubtilty may do well perchance in ſome other things; but not ſo well in articles of ſuch weight and conſequence.</p>
               <p>To goe on therefore in our intended method, before we come to particulars, of Chriſtian principles in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall we ſhall firſt ſay, That whatſoever among men profeſſing to hearken to reaſon, and endowed with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent judgement and diſcourſive faculties, either with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113795:8"/> any arguing at all will currantly paſſe; or upon ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry little arguing may be juſtified and approved for right or reaſonable, we reckon that in the number of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon principles: of which kind we take theſe three en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing particulars (to us here moſt conſiderable) to be,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>I.</abbr>
                  </note>Firſt, that there is a God.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>II.</abbr>
                  </note>Secondly, that the ways and counſels of God, there being ſuch diſproportion between God and man, muſt in all probability be different, in moſt things, from the thoughts, counſels, and apprehenſions of the wiſeſt of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>III.</abbr>
                  </note>Thirdly, that whatſoever hath been revealed by God himſelf unto man, ought to be beleeved and embraced by men, with as much fulneſſe of aſſent and beleef, as what is moſt certain and undoubted amongſt men, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grounded upon the ſenſes, or upon certain experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
               <p>To theſe, of which (as we ſhall ſhew) there can bee little queſtion amongſt rationall men, being all avou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and averred by principall authors of ſeverall ages and religions, whoſe writings remain to this day; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have not to doe here with Heathens or Infidels properly, but with ſuch as make no queſtion of the truth of the Scriptures, but ſtumble moſt, for want of due conſideration, as ſhall appear, at ſome of the former; we ſhall adde a fourth, which is,</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>IV.</abbr>
                  </note>That thoſe books of the Old and New Teſtament ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally received by all Chriſtians for Canonicall, were written by men inſpired of God, and juſtly accounted, <hi>The Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let us now conſider of theſe principles ſeverally, for it will much concern us that ſome of them that have
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113795:8"/> not been ſo throughly ſifted and conſidered of by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, be well cleared.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, that there is a God.<note place="margin">
                     <abbr>I.</abbr>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>We need not adde; by whom the world, and all that is in it, man particularly, was made: ſince it is the view and conſideration of the world eſpecially, and all that is in it, and man particularly, that brings a naturall man to the knowledge of God.<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.1, 2.</note> 
                  <hi>The heavens declare the glory of God, and the firmament ſheweth his handy work. Day unto day uttereth ſpeech, and night unto night uttereth knowledge.</hi> So the Pſalmiſt, inſpired by God, ſpeaketh of that knowledge of God, common to all men, (even them that know not God otherwiſe) by the bare evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and teſtimony of nature. And thereby we may the better know, that <hi>David</hi> was inſpired to ſay ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we finde others that were not inſpired, ſo general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and unanimouſly concurring in this acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Let thoſe Heathens be looked upon that have written <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>of the firſt apprehenſion,</hi> or <hi>diſcovery made by men of a Deity;</hi> as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Cleanthes,</hi> or <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> of old, whoſe names and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments are recorded by <hi>Tully,</hi> and by <hi>Sixtus Empiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus:</hi> or later writers, as <hi>Tully</hi> himſelfe, <hi>Plutarch, Dio Chryſoſtomus,</hi> and others; they all pitch upon this, as a principall evidence, <hi>aequabilitatem motus, converſione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li; ſolis, lunae, ſyderumque diſtinctionem, varietatem, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chritudinem, ordinem;</hi> that is in a word, <hi>The beauty, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, conſtancy of the Heavens, and Firmament, Sun and Moon, &amp;c.</hi> Even thoſe who moſt wickedly did ſet themſelves to argue againſt a <hi>Providence,</hi> could not but acknowledge this a ſtrong argument for Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: as <hi>Lucretius,</hi> an excellent Poet, but a profeſſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113795:9"/> Epicure, (in his opinions at leaſt) as when he ſaith;
<q>
                     <l>Sol &amp; luna ſuo luſtrantes lumine circum,</l>
                     <l>Perdocuere homines annorum tempora verti:</l>
                     <l>Et certa ratione geri rem atque ordine certo.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And again where he ſaith,
<q>
                     <l>Nam cum ſuſpicimus magni coeleſtia mundi</l>
                     <l>Templa ſuper, ſtelliſque micantibus aetherae fixum,</l>
                     <l>Et venit inmentem ſolis lunaeque viarum:</l>
                     <l>Tunc aliis oppreſſa malis in pectore cura</l>
                     <l>Illa quoque expergefactum caput erigere infit,</l>
                     <l>Ecquae forte Deum nobis immenſa poteſtas</l>
                     <l>Sit, vario motu quae candida ſydera verſet.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But whileſt we make the Heavens the chiefeſt and cleareſt evidence of a Deity, it muſt not be conceived, that they are the onely. For in very truth, there is not any thing ſo meane in ſhew and common eſtimation, which being throughly conſidered, doth not ſet out the power and wiſdome of God to a diſcerning eye: as by ancient Philoſophers, and others that have handled this argument is copiouſly ſhewed. Whence proceeded that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>Preſumption</hi> of all people and nations of the Univerſe, in acknowledging and worſhipping ſome Deity. Which conſideration above all others (this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall conſent and conſpiration of all men I mean) ſo farre moved <hi>Epicurus,</hi> that he was conſtrained thereby (as himſelf profeſſed) to acknowledge a Deity, though the uſe and conſequent of this acknowledgement hee did elude and fruſtrate by denying a Providence. <hi>Solus vidit Epicurus eſſe Deos, quod in omnium animis eorum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem impreſſiſſet ipſa natura:</hi> ſaith one of that ſect in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113795:9"/> 
                  <hi>Tully;</hi> that is, that <hi>Epicurus</hi> did firſt avouch the being of a Deity upon that ground of mankinds generall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; though even ſo it be not altogether true: but true it is, that <hi>Epicurus</hi> did much enlarge himſelf upon that one proof and argument, and was the firſt that applied the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to that purpoſe.</p>
               <p>But how, and how farre God may be found by the light of nature, is largely diſputed by the Schoolmen; and by thoſe that have written Metaphyſicks. Though all agree in the main, yet they are not all of one minde, neither concerning the extent, nor the clearneſſe of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall light. But to let them and their differences paſſe, the Apoſtle clearly determines it, and we with him,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>That the inviſible things of God from the Creation of the world are clearly ſeen, being underſtood by the things that are made, even his eternall power and Godhead, ſo that they are without excuſe.</hi> And certainly whoever ſhall weigh the arguments on both ſides, as in good order and with exactneſſe they are marſhalled by <hi>Sixtus Empiricus,</hi> a very learned man, and a Sceptique, that is, one that profeſſed himſelf to embrace no particular opinion, but to ſuſpend his judgement (and therefore to be hoped the more impartiall) in all things; will, or I am much deceived, even by evidence of reaſon (not to inſiſt upon his authority) think himſelf bound to be of Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> opinion. I think therefore I may conclude this point with Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> words, with little alteration: <hi>Quiſquis prodigia</hi> (ſaid he of the Chriſtian faith) <hi>adhuc ut credat inquirit, magnum eſt ipſe prodigium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de Civ. Dei l. <hi>22.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi> Initio.</note> 
                  <hi>qui mundo credente non credit:</hi> I ſay, <hi>Qui argumenta adhuc ut De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um credat, quaerit, &amp;c.</hi> To require proofs and arguments that there is a God, which all parts of this viſible world
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113795:10"/> doe ſo clearly declare, and all men of the world ſo free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acknowledge, muſt needs be an argument of as mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous ſtupor of minde, as it is of prodigious infidelity.</p>
               <p>As for the diſtinction of Perſons in the Deity, there be that affirm this myſtery not to have been unknown to ſome ancient Philoſophers. Divers plauſible paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and arguments they bring to that purpoſe, I confeſſe; and yet conceive nevertheleſſe, that by others it is more probably denyed. But however, this is quite another caſe, &amp; will not prove to our purpoſe here. That there is a God, with thoſe ordinary Attributes of Goodneſſe, &amp; Omnipotency, by ancient Heathens as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, is all wee deſire to be granted in the notion of a common notion and principle. And ſo much of the firſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>II.</abbr>
                  </note>The ſecond is, That the ways and counſels of God, &amp;c. as before.</p>
               <p>It was the firſt ſinne of man, that not contented with that ſimilitude of God, to which he was created by God, he aſpired to be like unto God in a higher and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable degree of likeneſſe. From which being ſhamefully and deſervedly diſappointed, it hath been his ſin and his infirmity ever ſince, that he hath endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured as much as in him lay to make God like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. From hence ſprang the making of Idols and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in his Politicks briefly noteth it in theſe words; <hi>That the gods doe reign</hi> (or, <hi>are governed by a King) is commonly ſaid and beleeved amongſt men, becauſe amongſt men are yet at this preſent, &amp; have been of old, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes; for as the ſhapes, ſo the lives of the gods, men are wont to liken unto their own.</hi> But <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> in his <hi>Stromata,</hi> partly out of <hi>Xenophanes</hi> an ancient Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, (miſcalled a Poet by ſome, becauſe he wrote in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113795:10"/> verſe) partly of himſelf, more largely, thus: <hi>The Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> (or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſaith he) <hi>as they do repreſent the gods like unto themſelves in outward ſhape, ſo in paſsions and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alſo. And as every nation</hi> (according to <hi>Xenophanes) make the gods to reſemble them in outward ſhape; (The Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopians, for example, form them black and flat noſed; the Thracians, flaxen haired</hi> [or, <hi>yellow haired] and skie colour eyed) ſo, their ſouls &amp; diſpoſitions alſo. The Barbarians make them cruell and terrible; the Grecians more meek and gentle, but yet not free from all perturbations of mind.</hi> So <hi>Clemens.</hi> The ſame obſervation is in <hi>Theodoret</hi> alſo, and in him, divers of <hi>Xenophanes</hi> own words and verſes. To this purpoſe <hi>Pliny</hi> alſo hath a notable paſſage in his <hi>Naturall Hiſtory,</hi> of a famous Painter in <hi>Rome</hi> about, or a little before <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his time; one <hi>Arellius:</hi> but his own words will doe beſt: <hi>Fuit</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>&amp; Arellius Romae celeber paulò ante Divum Auguſtum, niſi flagitio inſigni corrupiſſet artem; ſemper alicujus foeminae amore flagrans, &amp; ob id Deas pingens, ſed dilectarum imagine. Itaque in picturâ ejus ſcorta numerabantur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It hath ever been ſo, and is ſo to this day: and from this very fountain doe flow moſt of the groſſeſt opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſects in Religion, by which both the mindes of men are diſtracted, and the publique peace of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weals diſturbed. Every man is apt to think well of himſelf, of his own wit, reaſon, and judgement; and as he is, ſo muſt his god be, or he ſhall hardly bee his god. His own reaſon muſt be the rule of his gods rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and his wiſdome the rule of his gods wiſdome. I appeal to them that are verſed in controverſies, how often they ſhall meet with ſuch ſpeeches as theſe: It would not have ſtood with the wiſdome of God: with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113795:11"/> the goodneſſe of God: (yea and diſcretion too, ſome have ſaid) to have done this, ſaith one; not to have done it, ſaith another. In ſuch contradictions that both ſhould be in the right, every man knows is a thing im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible: ſo that the credit of God (if I may ſo ſpeak without blaſphemy) is put to the ſtake, and muſt needs ſuffer on the one ſide. Yea even in matters of no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, but of meer curioſity, there be that ſticke not at theſe expreſſions. So one, (and he a man of good account otherwiſe) except he may know all the particulars of <hi>Adams</hi> Paradiſe (about which how much controverſie and little certainty there is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. Eug.</hi> In Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſin p. <hi>23.</hi> b. Neque adeò in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanus fuerit Deus ut volue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hujus rei ignoratione per omnes aetates homines tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queri<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</note> is not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to them that have taken pains to enquire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it) he charges God with unkindneſſe and inhuma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. I muſt confeſſe of my ſelf that I never read ſuch ſpeeches without ſome horror; nor ever made any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther account of them then of ſpeeches approaching to blaſphemy: neither can I perſwade my ſelf they ever had any very right apprehenſion of the Majeſty of God, that make their own wiſdome, goodneſſe, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiocination the modell of his. The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> I am ſure hath taught us to think better of God then ſo. But why ſay I the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah?</hi> they are Gods own words concerning himſelf:<note place="margin">Eſay 55.89.</note> 
                  <hi>For my thoughts are not your thoughts, neither are your wayes my ways, ſaith the Lord. For as the heavens are higher then the earth, ſo are my ways higher then your ways, and my thoughts, then your thoughts.</hi> To this purpoſe alſo are the words of the Pſalmiſt,<note place="margin">Pſ. 77.19.</note> as they are expounded by many: <hi>Thy way is in the Sea, and thy path in the great waters, and thy foot-ſteps are not known.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it is not Scripture that we have here to do with, but common notions, and principles of humane reaſon.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113795:11"/> To humane reaſon therfore, &amp; to common ſenſe I appeal; If God be acknowledged infinite, omnipotent, (as by the Creation of the world he may be inferred) will not as much difference between God and man be granted, as is between man and brutes? Or at leaſt (becauſe I know what may be objected) betweene a man and a childe? The ſame man when he is come to maturity of years and diſcretion; and when he was but a childe, or a boy? Or as much as is between an extraordinary wiſe, learned and experienced man; &amp; an ordinary, plain, ruſtick capacity? How many things ſeem ſtrange, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable, incredible, impoſſible to the one, which to the others are well known to be nothing ſo? Of <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clitus</hi> the Philoſopher his writings ſome-body once ſaid, as I remember, <hi>What he underſtood he liked very well; what he did not, he verily beleeved was as good.</hi> And can it be that any man ſhould owe leſſe civility to God? To this very purpoſe <hi>Plotinus</hi> the Philoſopher, if my memory deceive me not, hath a pregnant paſſage. The teſtimonies alſo of divers Heathens, Philoſophers and others, concerning the weakneſſe and imbecillity of mans underſtanding to comprehend things divine, we could produce. But becauſe <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> is generally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged to have been as a Favourite, ſo a great Patron of nature, we will content our ſelves here with his ingenuous acknowledgement. In his Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks, (by him called ſometimes <hi>Theology</hi>) ſpeaking in a place of the difficulty of that Science, he hath theſe words:<note place="margin">Ariſt. Metaph. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Ed. in fol. p. <hi>856.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>It being ſo that the difficulty of a thing may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken two ways, it may be that the cauſe of it is not in the things themſelves, but in us. For as the eyes of Bats are to the light of the Sun when it is day</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>ſo is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113795:12"/> the intellect of our ſouls to the knowledge of thoſe things, which of themſelves are moſt clear and perſpicuous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How unreaſonable it is to judge of the ways or works of God, by humane either faculties or affections, by what hath been ſaid, may appear: how dangerous it is, though that alſo in part hath appeared, yet becauſe it is a point that I would have well cleared, I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in one particular more. We ſay commonly, one good turn deſerveth another: and ſo indeed it is, for the moſt part. There be but few whoſe goodneſſe is not in ſome reſpect or other, if not meerly mercenary, yet mixed with a by-reſpect to themſelves, and their owne intereſt. Among men, it is ſo: whereupon <hi>Epicurus</hi> infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that it muſt be ſo in God too. And becauſe he could not conceive, (right enough in that, according to the Pſalmiſt;<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.2.</note> 
                  <hi>My goodneſſe extendeth not to thee: but to the Saints that are in the earth</hi>) how man could merit at the hands of God; another groſſe conceit of his, (and that too grounded upon the ſimilitude of mans weakneſſe) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring, that God could not take care of man, or of the world in generall, without much trouble and diſtraction to himſelf; it made him to deny a Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. Of this latter, the writings of the Epicureans are full: it was their chiefeſt Theme. As for the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, I appeal to <hi>Lucretius,</hi> one of <hi>Epicurus</hi> his greateſt Champions;
<q>
                     <l>—Quid enim immortalibus atque beatis,</l>
                     <l>Gratia noſtra queat largirier emolumenti;</l>
                     <l>Vt tantum noſtrâ cauſâ gerere aggrediantur?</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall not need to ſay more concerning this ſecond principle. I had not ſaid ſo much of it, but that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113795:12"/> it of great importance to us, as will appear in the progreſſe of this <hi>Diſcourſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third is, That whatſoever hath been revealed,<note place="margin">
                     <abbr>III.</abbr>
                  </note> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The matter is thus ſtated by <hi>Gregory Nazianz.</hi> in his <hi>Invectives</hi> againſt <hi>Julian,</hi> who ſcoffed at the Chriſtians for their uſual Motto, <hi>Beleeve;</hi> ſaying, that all their wit &amp; wiſdom was included in that one word: After divers other things by him alledged and retorted upon <hi>Julian,</hi> he thus proceeds: <hi>By that word,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>we profeſſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, that it is not lawfull for us to diſtruſt, or diſcredit any thing that is averred by men divinely inſpired: and that the credit of ſuch, with us is ſuch that we account their bare word a ſufficient demonſtration, farre beyond all argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and evidences of humane ratiocination.</hi> So he there; and ſo others, whom I ſhall not need to name. Now this principle of beleef grounded upon divine revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as in one reſpect I grant it may be accounted the proper principle of Chriſtianity, becauſe no Religion or Science can juſtly pretend to ſuch a foundation but Chriſtianity; ſo, generally conſidered, why it ſhould, as by many it is made, be more proper to Chriſtians, then to other men, I ſee no ſufficient reaſon. For how can it bee conceived, that any man or people in the world that really beleeve a Deity or divine nature, ſhould make any queſtion of the truth of thoſe things which iſſue from ſuch a nature? <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>Who can bee ſo ſimple, or ſo phrentick rather?</hi> ſaith <hi>Theodoret.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if any man apprehend it otherwiſe, yet approved experience will convince him. In what eſteem Oracles were anciently amongſt all Nations, no man can be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113795:13"/> that is not a ſtranger to all Hiſtories: whence proceeded the Proverb, <hi>Tanquam ex tripode,</hi> of thoſe things which are of unqueſtionable credit or certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. From the ſame Origine as the Oracles, iſſued alſo their <hi>aruſpicina, auſpicia, omina,</hi> and other ſuch ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in ſome ſort or other received and practiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt all Nations: profeſſing by that how deſirous and ready they were to be guided and directed in their ways, at leaſt in their moſt important affairs, by them who could ſee into things future with better then mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall eyes.</p>
               <p>Upon this ground, politick wiſe men, as <hi>Numa Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilius, Lycurgus,</hi> and divers others mentioned in ancient Hiſtories, to make the people the more pliable to their laws and inſtitutions, deviſed means how to poſſeſſe them with an opinion, that they entertained ſome commerce with ſome Deity or other, by which they were prompted to ſuch and ſuch things. Whether the Romans did not make ſuch a uſe of their <hi>Sibylles</hi> verſes, or whether they really beleeved of them themſelves, what they perſwaded others to beleeve, I will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, becauſe either way it ſhews how ready men have been generally to yeeld aſſent and obedience to divine revelation. Hence is that obſervation of Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,<note place="margin">Quiat. Curt. l. <hi>4.</hi> Ed. Pariſ. p. <hi>74.</hi>
                  </note> which many more largely inſiſt upon, by <hi>Quint. Curtius,</hi> thus briefly contracted: <hi>Nullares efficatiùs mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudinem regit, quàm ſuperſtitio. Alioquin impotens, Java, murabilis, ubi vanâ religione eapta eſt, meliùs vatibus quàm ducibus ſuis parent;</hi> that is, <hi>There is not any thing more powerfull to rule the people then ſuperſtition,</hi> (or <hi>an opinion of religion) which otherwiſe of it ſelf being unru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wild, and mutable, when it is poſſeſſed with an opinion of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113795:13"/> religion, it will ſooner be commanded by their Prophets, then by their Captains.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This may be further confirmed by the doctrine of the ancient Maſters of Rhetorick, who where they treat of authorities, (as they call them) that are brought by Oratours and Advocates for the confirmation of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny cauſe, give the firſt place to thoſe teſtimonies which they call <hi>divina teſtimonia. Ponitur à quibuſdam</hi> (ſaith <hi>Quintilian) &amp; quidem in parte primâ Deorum auctoritas, quae eſt ex reſponſis, ut Socratem eſſe ſapientiſsimum.</hi> And a little after, <hi>Quae cùm propria cauſae ſunt, divina teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia vocantur: cum aliunde accerſuntur, argumenta.</hi> True it is that theſe <hi>divina teſtimonia,</hi> (as the ſame Authour ſheweth elſewhere) were not generally received among the Heathens. But the reaſon was, partly becauſe there were then many of <hi>Epicurus</hi> his ſect, who denyed a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and that the gods entermedled with humane affairs, and ſo eluded all ſuch authorities as falſe and counterfait; and partly becauſe moſt were ſo in very truth, either meerly forged and pretended; or ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure and ambiguous, as that nothing could certainly be concluded from them.</p>
               <p>From what hath been ſaid, doth ſufficiently appear what hath been the common opinion of men concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing divine revelation. Though this may ſuffice, yet I will adde one paſſage or two of ancient Philoſophers, which goe further yet, and may give further content to them who are not altogether unacquainted with the writings of ſuch.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> in his ſecond <hi>Aleibiades,</hi> (a Dialogue of his ſo called) the ſubject whereof is altogether <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Of Prayer,</hi> having diſputed at large how hard a thing it is to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113795:14"/> to pray well, and inſiſted upon ſome particular forms, concludes (in the perſon of <hi>Socrates) that they muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and wait, untill ſome other teach them</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>doccat,</hi> here, not <hi>diſcat) how they muſt be affected,</hi> (or, <hi>how they ought to carry themſelves) both towards God &amp; men. Yea, but when ſhal that time be</hi> (replyeth <hi>Alcibiades) &amp; who is he that ſhal teach us? for gladly would I ſee that man.</hi> And upon <hi>Socrates</hi> his return, that it <hi>is one that will take care of him, and take away that miſt from his eyes, that hindereth him from the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of that, which is truly good or evil: Alcibiades</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludeth, that he is <hi>fully reſolved, to ſubmit unto that man, whatſoever he ſhall enjoyn him, whereby he may be bettered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This paſſage of <hi>Plato</hi> is much made of not by alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorizing <hi>Platonicks</hi> onely, who often give ſcope to their phanſies upon very little ground of reaſon or probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; but by more ſober unpartiall men alſo. Among others, a learned man, who hath taken great pains upon <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> and out of his affection to <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> may be thought by ſome to have paſſed but a harſh cenſure up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Plato,</hi> notwithſtanding this his generall judgement, inſtances in divers particulars, wherein he acknowledges him to deſerve more then ordinary commendation: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others, in this very particular which we have ſpoken of; in theſe very words: <hi>Quod docuerit, &amp;c. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nique quod omninò mirum eſt, &amp;c.</hi> that is in Engliſh, <hi>As for other things, ſo particularly (which is to be admired in him) that he did teach the ineffable Incarnation, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of our Lord Chriſt, and did in a manner preſage</hi> (or, <hi>foreſee) the Doctrine of the Goſpel, when he ſaid, that men muſt acquieſce for a while to his inſtructions and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, untill a more venerable</hi> (or <hi>majeſtick) man, and more ſacred, who would open all ſacraries and fountains of truth,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113795:14"/> ſhould appear upon Earth: whom, as one that could not erre, all men ſhould bee bound to follow. For who elſe by this more majeſtick, more ſacred man, can be meant, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So he of that place: which though he doth not quote, yet by what others ſay of it to the ſame purpoſe, and becauſe I know no other in all <hi>Plato</hi> that comes neerer, I am confident is the place he ſo much commendeth. Yet there be that make a queſtion whether <hi>Socrates</hi> himſelf were not the man intended by <hi>Plato:</hi> which ſome of the words would bear well enough; but the greater part, not; as I conceive. However if any que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion be made of this place, there be others in <hi>Plato</hi> no leſſe admirable, and leſſe queſtionable. Such a one is to be found in his <hi>Phaedon:</hi> where having diſcourſed of ſome opinions (ridiculous enough, at the beſt, but made worſe by miſtake) concerning the ſtate of the ſoul after death, he concludes, that <hi>to know the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty</hi> (they are his very words) <hi>of thoſe things in this life, is either altogether impoſsible, or very difficult: that nevertheleſſe it is the part of a generous man, not to give over ſearching, untill he have met with the truth; or ſo much of it at leaſt, as by indefatigable induſtry is to be attained: That ſo,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>venturing our ſelves in the Cockboat, as it were, of the ſafeſt and moſt exact diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very that can be made by man, we may wade through this mortall life, and think our ſelves happy in this condition, untill a more firm bottome of divine Word</hi> (or, <hi>Oracle) hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen unto us, wherein with more ſafety and ſecurity we may be carried over.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In thoſe words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by ſome tranſlated, <hi>divine Oracle,</hi> doth properly ſignifie, <hi>divine Word:</hi> which ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to whom it is appropriated by ſacred Authors, no
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113795:15"/> Chriſtian, I hope, needeth to be told.</p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Plato,</hi> in that ſo much admired peece, which <hi>Tully</hi> of old tranſlated into Latin, his <hi>Timeus,</hi> in a place, where he ſpeaks of <hi>daemons,</hi> or ſpirits; or rather excuſeth himſelf that he doth not ſpeak of them, referring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to ancient tradition; he ſaith there, as <hi>Tully</hi> hath rendred him, <hi>Credendum eſt nimirum veteribus &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcis, ut aiunt, viris, qui ſe progeniem Deorum eſſe dicebant.</hi> And few words after, <hi>Ac difficillimum factu</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in <hi>Plato) à Diis ortis fidem non habere, quanquam nec argumentis nec rationibus certis eorum oratio confirmetur: ſed quia de ſuis rebus notis videntur loqui,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plato <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> v. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſer cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ariſt. <hi>1.</hi> Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſ. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>veteri legi mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que parendum eſt:</hi> that is, <hi>It is very hard</hi> (or, <hi>unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) not to beleeve them who are deſcended from the gods, though their ſpeech</hi> (or, <hi>doctrine) be not confirmed by any arguments or certain proofs. But foraſmuch as they ſpake of their own things beſt known unto them, we muſt ſubmit to the old law, and rule.</hi> There will be found in theſe words not much leſſe then in thoſe of <hi>Nazianzene,</hi> which at the beginning of this third Obſervation we ſpake of, if they be compared.</p>
               <p>And again in another place of the ſame <hi>Timeus,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpoken of the firſt principles of things, <hi>But as for theſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>what was their originall from the very firſt beginning, God knoweth, and among men, ſuch as are beloved of him;</hi> (or, <hi>dear unto him</hi>) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I take notice of the words (beſides the ſenſe) becauſe of Chriſt his words, <hi>John</hi> 15.14, 15. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. Ye are my friends, if ye doe whatſoever I command you. Henceforth I call you not ſervants, for the ſervant know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not what his Lord doth: but I have called you friends: for all things that I have heard of my Father, I have made known unto you.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113795:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>If all theſe places being put together contain not a propheſie concerning Chriſt, <hi>The Word of God, the Son of God,</hi> who <hi>was made fleſh,</hi> and came into the world, as to redeem the world by the oblation of his own body, ſo alſo to reveal the truth of God unto men; if all theſe places, I ſay, being put together doe not amount to a propheſie, I know not we may call a propheſie. Sure we are there is nothing forged or ſuppoſititious in all this; which of the <hi>Sibyls</hi> (that collection of verſes I mean, which now goeth under that name) and of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curius Triſmegiſtus</hi> hath been proved.</p>
               <p>For a cloſe of this third point or principle, I ſhall add a paſſage of <hi>Dio Chryſoſtomus,</hi> a famous Oratour and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, who lived in <hi>Trajanus</hi> the Emperour his days, and was in great account with him; whoſe words al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, becauſe he was a great <hi>Platoniſt,</hi> may be ſome light to thoſe of <hi>Plato's.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All the diſcourſes, and all the devices of men are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to divine inſpiration, and revelation,</hi> (or, <hi>authority.) For what traditions</hi> (or, <hi>doctrines) ſoever concerning the gods and this Vniverſe, that are not void of wiſdome and truth, have been among men, all ſuch were begotten in the ſouls of men by divine will, and by a ſpeciall lot,</hi> (or, <hi>luck, Gr.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>as may bee knowne by them that were the firſt Prophets and Profeſſors of Divinity; ſuch as</hi> Orpheus, <hi>ſon to one of the</hi> Muſes, <hi>is reported to have been in</hi> Thracia; <hi>and another certain Shepheard in</hi> Boecria, <hi>taught by the</hi> Muſes. <hi>And whoſoever they be that take upon them to vent any doctrine of their own abroad for true, without divine rapture, or inſpiration, their doctrine is certainly both abſurd and wicked.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth is,<note place="margin">
                     <abbr>IV.</abbr>
                  </note> That thoſe books of the Old and New Teſtament, &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113795:16"/>
               <p>I ſaid before, I preſuppoſed I had to doe here with Chriſtians, who were already ſatisfied concerning the truth of thoſe books. It is well known that ſuch have been of old, and are at this day, too many, who though they profeſſe to admit and allow for divine the ſame Scriptures that we doe, and pretend to the faith and doctrine therein contained, as much as we; yet do not beleeve of Chriſt as we doe. I have no direct aim at them in this Diſcourſe, intended only for the further ſatisfaction and confirmation of Orthodoxe Chriſtians in this main point: no direct aim, I ſay, but as the hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of this argument upon Scripture grounds, may prove a conviction of their impiety and infidelity. As for them that profeſſe againſt this ground of either Old or New Teſtament, which we build upon, they will not, neither directly or indirectly, come within our reach.</p>
               <p>But how then, (may ſome object perchance) can we, as we firſt maintained, give a rationall account of our faith, and ſtop the mouths of Atheiſts and Infidels, if we cannot prove the Scriptures to be the Word of God, upon common grounds of humane reaſon, and ratiocination? To which we anſwer, that although we doe not apprehend thoſe grounds ſo evident and ſo uncontrollable, as to oblige every rationall man, to a preſent and ready aſſent, and therefore not to be reckoned among thoſe common notions (though re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducible to them) and principles we have ſpoken of: yet that the Scriptures by them that are learned may be maintained upon grounds of reaſon ſufficient to convince and to convert an Infidel who with ſimplicity of heart, without ſtrong prejudice or worldly engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113795:16"/> to the contrary, doth ſeek the truth, we doe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to beleeve, and ſhould be ſorry (were it our aim, or argument) if we could not make it good.</p>
               <p>One argument onely I ſhall inſiſt upon here, which by ancient Chriſtians, as being both popular (proper I mean for vulgar capacities) and ſolid, was much preſſed, and whereof they found good uſe. The teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of a known profeſſed enemy, or adverſary, hath always among all men been accounted a very pregnant evidence. And what relation there is between the Old and New Teſtament, is well known to all Chriſtians, and may ſoon be demonſtrated to them that are not. Now then what greater evidence of the truth of the Old Teſtament can any man require, then the Jewes, our greateſt and moſt malicious adverſaries? Then the Jews, I ſay, who by a ſpeciall Providence, though ſcattered and diſperſed through the whole world con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to this day a diſtinct Nation from all other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the world, and to this day ſo zealous for <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and all other Scriptures of the Old Teſtament, that in all places, for teſtimony of the truth of thoſe Scriptures, they are ready, if they be put to it, to lay down their lives, and to forgoe whatſoever is deareſt unto them. Whoſe predeceſſors alſo (that too, by a ſpeciall admirable Providence) have been of old ſo curious and ſo provident for the preſervation of thoſe Scriptures which they acknowledged, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed an art (of which art either for invention or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curatneſſe there is no parallel in all the ancient lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Heathens how to prevent not the loſſe of it onely, but the corruption alſo, by any either addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or diminution, or alteration; in words, or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113795:17"/> ſyllables, yea letters, and tittles.</p>
               <p>How much this argument of the Jews teſtimony was made of by the ancients, and of what conſequence it then proved, may appear by Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who ſpeaks of it in ſundry places of his Works. In the twelfth of his books againſt the <hi>Manicheans,</hi> he ſaith; <hi>Quid enim eſt aliud hodieque gens ipſa Judaeorum, niſi quaedam ſcriniaria Chriſtianorum, baſulans leges &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetas ad teſtimonium aſſertionis Eccleſiae?</hi> that is: <hi>For what to this day are the Jews, but as it were the regiſters</hi> (or, <hi>record-keepers) of the Chriſtians, bearing up &amp; down the Law and the Prophets with them for a teſtimony to the Church?</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in theſe words doth allude to the cuſtome of the Jews, who then in every Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue were wont (and uſe it in moſt places, I beleeve to this day) to have ſacred cheſts, or desks, wherein to keep their holy Bible, not onely for its ſafety, but in reverence to it alſo. What Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> cals <hi>Scrini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, Tertullian</hi> inditeth, <hi>armarium,</hi> in his <hi>De Habitumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liebri, ch.</hi> 3. And <hi>Epiphanius</hi> in his Treatiſe, <hi>De Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deribus &amp; menſuris,</hi> where he treateth of the difference of Canonicalll books from others, he uſeth the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Such books</hi> (ſaith he ſpeaking of that which is called <hi>Wiſdome,</hi> and others of like nature) <hi>are accounted by them uſefull and profitable, but are not in the number</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>of the Canonicall: for which cauſe alſo they are not laid up</hi> (with the Canonicall) <hi>in the aron,</hi> that is, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>in the cheſt or capſe of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lamp. Alardi, Epiphyll. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olog.</note>I wonder that any man could ſo miſtake <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> as though he had beleeved that the whole Jews Bible, or Old Teſtament, had been kept in the Ark where the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113795:17"/> two Tables containing the ten Commandements, were appointed to be laid; which Ark, before the ſaid Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament was compleat, ever ſince the Babylonian Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity had been wanting. <hi>Petavius</hi> himſelf, a learned Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite that hath ſet out <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> except he may be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to expunge thoſe words as ſpurious, (the laſt refuge of venturous Criticks, when they are plunged, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not get out) doth plainly profeſſe to ſuſpect this to have been the opinion of <hi>Epiphanius:</hi> whereas we have more occaſion to ſuſpect of him, that he did not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand him, or had any thought of thoſe paſſages of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> which would have made <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanius</hi> his meaning clear enough, and as we conceive, unqueſtionable.</p>
               <p>I have now done with thoſe grounds of common no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and principles of humane reaſon, the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whereof I conceived would be proper and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to the ſubject we are to treat of: a ſubject of it ſelf ſo ſublime and ſo farre above the reach of humane underſtanding, that whoever takes upon him to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with it, had need to lay wel his grounds before-hand, and carefully to circumſcribe himſelf, leſt he fall into extravagances, before he be aware. <hi>Qui ſcrutatur Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtatem, opprimetur à gloriâ,</hi> whether that were <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi> meaning, <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.27. or no, may be controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; but a true ſentence it is however, and they ſhall be ſure to find it true, that proceed not, in ſuch argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with much warineſſe.</p>
               <p>This method of proceeding by certain <hi>hypotheſes</hi> laid for a foundation, though it be moſt proper to <hi>Mathematicians,</hi> yet it is not unuſuall to other Artiſts and Writers. It is the very method uſed by <hi>Plato</hi> in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113795:18"/> his <hi>Timeus,</hi> the ſubject whereof is the Creation of the world, of man particularly: our ſubject is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration, or regeneration of mankinde, in Chriſt: which of the two, is generally accounted the greater work.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:113795:18"/>
               <head>OF THE INCARNATION of CHRIST.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ncient Philoſophers that have written con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the nature of this Univerſe, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve this as a great myſtery of nature, and a ſingular evidence of the power and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God (the author of nature) that whatſoever is commonly ſaid to <hi>dye,</hi> or to <hi>periſh,</hi> is by this death, or corruption (which they more properly call <hi>alteration</hi>) the cauſe of the production and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of ſomething elſe: whereby the courſe of this worlds generation in generall, is continued and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
               <p>It may be applied (in ſome kinde) to this ſacred ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject and myſtery of Chriſt his <hi>Incarnation.</hi> The fall and miſcarrying of the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> was the cauſe or occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the leaſt, of the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi> Had not the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> (the firſt fruits of mankind, in whom the whole lump was either to be ſanctified or polluted) ſinned, and by his ſin undone all that ſhould come from him; the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>according to the fleſh,</hi> as the Scripture ſpeaketh, had never been born; for there had been no need of him. For as for the conceits of ſome either ancient Hereticks, or later Schoolmen, who have maintained a contrary opinion, as neither grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Scripture, nor any probability of reaſon, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113795:19"/> rejected by the more ſober of all ſides, I willingly paſſe by.</p>
               <p>But on the other ſide, though the Incarnation of the Son of God, of all the works of God hath eminently the preeminence, yet we may not ſay or think, that therefore the firſt man ſinned, or was ordained to ſin, that the Son of God might be incarnated. For ſo wee ſhould make God the author of ſin, then which, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing either in it ſelf can be more deteſtable, or more contrary to true piety. God indeed to whom all things paſt, preſent &amp; future are equally preſent, as hee foreſaw from all eternity the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> and in him of all mankinde; ſo did he from all eternity decree the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of his Son for the reſtauratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man. Whence are thoſe phraſes of Scripture, that Chriſt (as a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer</hi>)<note n="a" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.20.</note> 
                  <hi>was fore-ordained before the foundation of the world:</hi> that we were<note n="b" place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> 
                  <hi>choſen,</hi> or<note n="c" place="margin">2 Tim. 1.9.</note> 
                  <hi>ſaved,</hi> (in Chriſt) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the foundation of the world;</hi> or, <hi>before the world began:</hi> and again, that Chriſt is the<note n="d" place="margin">Apoc. 13.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Lamb ſlain from the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the world:</hi> though as for this laſt paſſage, I rather embrace their interpretation, (ſuch <hi>hyperbaton's,</hi> as they call them, being very frequent in the Scriptures) who referre this <hi>from the beginning of the world,</hi> to <hi>the book of life</hi> (as <hi>Apocal.</hi> 17.18.) rather then to <hi>the Lamb ſlain:</hi> though I muſt profeſſe againſt the reaſon that is given by ſome (as <hi>Ribera</hi> the Jeſuite, upon the place) as though there were any abſurdity or incongruity in the ſpeech, being ſo juſtifiable by other parallel places of Scripture. But this foreſight of God did no ways occaſion, much leſſe neceſſitate the diſobedience of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> who as he was created with perfect freedome of will, ſo he might (had not he been wanting to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113795:19"/> have reſiſted the temptation of the Devill, and have continued in that innocency, to which, his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and immortality was annexed. But it ſo fell out, that <hi>Adam</hi> uſed his freewill to his own, and all that ſhould be after him, being deſcended from him, their ruine, and eternall confuſion. Better it had been for him certainly, and better for all that had any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence of him, never to have been, (for I am not of their opinion that think any beeing better then no beeing) then to ſee himſelf at once ſtript of his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and innocency: of the ſon of God, become the ſlave of the Devill: and beſides his own perſonall mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, the occaſion of ſo much evill unto others.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Seneca</hi> De Clem. l. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to autem non naſci melius, quàm numerari inter publico malo natos?</hi> how much more then <hi>quàm unum omnis omnibus mali cauſam extitiſſe?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here a queſtion offers it ſelf; though we would be very cautelous of moving queſtions of this nature, where the Scripture it ſelf is ſilent, too much curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in this kind having been the occaſion of ſundry blaſphemies and hereſies; yet becauſe there is ſome ground for it in the Scripture, we may not altogether paſſe it by. The queſtion is, Why God would permit <hi>Adam</hi> to ſin, which he might many ways have preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, if he had thought fit.</p>
               <p>The firſt anſwer is, becauſe it became God well, (if this be not too bold a ſpeech) to make good his own order, and to maintain his owne work. It had pleaſed God to endow <hi>Adam</hi> with a perfect free-will. He was furniſhed with ſufficient grace to continue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and to withſtand ſin; but that grace was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall; as be uſed it, as he liked it, he might either
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113795:20"/> improve it, or loſe it. If therefore we muſt make a queſtion of it, it is more proper to ask why God cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>Adam</hi> with free-will, then why God did not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſin of <hi>Adam,</hi> being ſo created. This very que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion much troubled ancient Philoſophers, who had the bare light of reaſon and nature for their guide; Why God being ſo perfectly good, as they did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him, would ſuffer ſin and wickedneſſe in men and among men either at all, or ſo far to prevail. They commonly diſtinguiſh of ſeverall degrees, or kinds of creatures with relation to goodneſſe, by God created: the laſt kinde whereof (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is their word) are thoſe, whoſe condition is to be mutable; to fall, and to riſe again; ſometimes to look upwards unto the fountain of good; ſometimes to be ſwayed downwards by the contagion of the body, and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of the world: and their determination upon the matter is, that neither the power nor the wiſdom of Almighty God would, or could ſo much have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, if this kind alſo (this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) had not been. What they ſay, being grounded upon no better autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, then humane ratiocination, will not much concern us, but to check our impiety, if neither reaſon, (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended unto us with the advantage of ſuch prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents) nor religion, (grounded upon certain revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) can doe that in us, which bare and naked reaſon could in them; to make us, if not to plead for our Creator by ſtrength of arguments; yet to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him good and wiſe in all his ways, even beyond our underſtandings, and where our reaſon is at a ſtand.</p>
               <p>Another reaſon is given, becauſe God having in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf predetermined the redemption of collapſed man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:113795:20"/> by the Incarnation of his Son, he therefore left <hi>Adam</hi> to the liberty of his will, and the Devill of his malice, becauſe no other way can be conceived how he might more effectually have demonſtrated and revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led at once, unto men and Angels the infiniteneſſe both of his goodneſſe and of his juſtice: as we ſhall have occaſion afterwards to ſhew more at large.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Adam</hi> then (and in him <hi>humana natura,</hi> or mankind in generall) being ſo created by God, and through the temptation of the Devill, and his own wretchedneſſe (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Greek Fathers uſually call it, that is, <hi>looſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and remiſneſſe of the minde,</hi> accompanied with care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe and ſecurity) ſo lapſed; it pleaſed Almighty God in the depth of his goodneſſe and wiſdome, to appoint his reſtauration by the Incarnation of his Son, that eternall Word, by whom he had made, as all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, ſo man particularly: that is, That his Son, coeternall with him, and from all eternity (by an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible myſtery) begotten by him, ſhould in the fulneſſe of time be made fleſh: that is, aſſume the nature of man unto himſelf, into a perfect Union (but without mixture or confuſion) of two natures in one perſon: that ſo united, and ſo incarnated, he might offer himſelf, by his Paſſion, (Chriſt, as God &amp; Man, though not in his Deity, ſuffering) unto God, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as a ſufficient ranſome, in his ſtricteſt juſtice, for the ſins of all men: to the end, that <hi>whoſoever ſhould beleeve in him</hi> ſo incarnated, and by a lively faith lay hold on the merits of his death, <hi>might not periſh,</hi> but as a true member of his myſticall body, <hi>might have in him everlaſting life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How Chriſt, the eternall Son of God, came to be the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113795:21"/> ſon of a woman, as it doth deeply concern us not to be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of what the Scriptures have revealed unto us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it, ſo to goe beyond that, I conceive no leſſe dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. The Scriptures ſay, as we have it in our Creed, that he was conceived of the holy Ghoſt, &amp; born of the <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyn Mary:</hi> and the words of the Angel to the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin are known,<note place="margin">Luke 1.35.</note> 
                  <hi>The Holy Ghoſt ſhall come upon thee, &amp; the power of the Higheſt ſhall overſhadow thee; therefore alſo that Holy thing that ſhall be born of thee, ſhall be called the Son of God.</hi> If any man venture beyond this in diſcourſing the manner, how; I dare not follow him. It is obſerved, (and obſervable indeed) that in this myſtery Chriſt is not ſo properly ſaid to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten;</hi> (though that word alſo be uſed ſometimes (as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, made: as not <hi>begotten</hi> of the ſubſtance or eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Holy Ghoſt, (as ordinarily children are of the ſubſtance of their fathers) but made by the power of the Holy Ghoſt, of the ſubſtance of the <hi>Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> onely. Whereupon ancient Fathers were wont to ſay, that as Chriſt in regard of his eternall generation is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>without a Mother;</hi> ſo in regard of his temporall, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, <hi>without a Father.</hi> There is good uſe of this obſervation againſt thoſe hereticks of old, and the Anabaptiſts of later times, who though they could not agree among themſelves, how Chriſt came to have a body, whether true, or imaginary, and the like; yet agreed in this, to deny that he was made of the ſubſtance of a woman.</p>
               <p>This is the myſtery of which we may truly ſay, that it is <hi>The chiefeſt of the ways of God.</hi> That the juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of any one ſinner, is a greater work then the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the world in generall, is by many maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113795:21"/> and divers reaſons are given for it. I durſt not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake for the ſolidity of all thoſe reaſons (thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, that are drawn from this very particular of Chriſt his Incarnation) that are given: but certainly this myſtery of the Son of God his Incarnation, is ſo tranſcendent a miracle above all other miracles of the world, whether Creation, or any other, as that wee may juſtly doubt, whether he truly beleeve it, or ever took it into ſerious conſideration, who in compariſon of this, doth admire any thing elſe. For as for thoſe things that are commonly moſt admired, and for the wonderfulneſſe by divers thought incredible, if a man ſhall rationally conſider of them, they will not ſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in very deed. It is the ſaying of an ancient Father, (one of the moſt learned and rationall of thoſe times) that there is but one true miracle in the world, and that is, an Omnipotent God. Having inſtanced in ſome one particular, which among the many ſtrange ſights of this world, he thought might ſeem as ſtrange as any; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith he;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodor The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapeut. l. 3.</hi> Sed ibi Latinus interpres men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem verborum non aſſecutus eſt: non ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſit certè.</note> 
                  <hi>a miracle above a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle:</hi> and preſently, (upon better conſideration, as it were) he doth correct himſelf. <hi>And yet I dare ſay</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>that the miracle, is no miracle: For God, to whom al things, that he can think convenient, are eaſie, being the author,</hi> (or, <hi>workman) we have much reaſon to glorifie the author, but no reaſon at all to wonder at the matter.</hi> He gives the reaſon in another place: <hi>That any thing ſhould be, (whether by generation, or creation) whereof a cauſe</hi> (God, that is, the ſupream cauſe) <hi>can be given, right reaſon will eaſily allow of. But that any thing ſhould bee without a cauſe</hi> (as God onely is) <hi>no reaſon can comprehend.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:113795:22"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vos enim ipſi dicere ſoletis, nihil eſſe quod Deus efficere non poſſit, &amp; quidem ſine labore ullo; ut enim hominum membra nulla conten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ione, mente ipſâ ac v luntate moveantur, ſic numine Deorum omnia fingi, moveri, muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rique poſſe: neque id dicitis ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>osè atque aniliter, ſed phyſicâ conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique ratione. Materiam enim rerum, in quâ &amp; ex quâ omnia ſint, totam eſſe flexib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lem &amp; commutabilem, ut nihil ſit quod non ex eâ quamvis ſubitò ſingi convertique poſſit: ejus autem univerſae fict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icem &amp; moderatricem di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinam eſſe providentiam. <hi>Cic. de Nat. Deorum.</hi>
                  </note>And indeed this Omnipotency of God ſome Heathen Philoſophers have acknowledged, and expreſſed it very well, likening it to the power of the ſoul over the members of the body, which members upon the leaſt <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or intimation of the mind turne and move with all readineſſe and faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. Now God, ſaid they, is the ſoul, or mind of this Univerſe, all parts and parcels whereof are at his beck, and diſpoſall, to be turned into any ſhape or form at his pleaſure, with as much eaſe and facility, as the members of our bodies are ſwayed by the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and commands of our minds. This therefore granted, that there is a God, and he (as in reaſon it will be ſuppoſed) omnipotent, all things that imply not contradiction (for ſuch rather argue weaknes, then power) to ſuch a one muſt needs be of equall facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. It is the faſhion of men to wonder at thoſe things onely that are not uſuall: that is, (as I intend it here) that are not, or happen not according to that order or courſe of nature, which Omnipotent God in his wiſdome thought fit at the beginning of the world to eſtabliſh. And indeed as God did not eſtabliſh that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at the firſt for nothing; that is, to break it without ſome extraordinary cauſe: ſo there is no reaſon that thoſe things ſhould eaſily be beleeved, which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the ordinary courſe of nature; untill certain e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, or divine revelation (the beſt evidence) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force our faith. But if thoſe things be conſidered in themſelves with relation to the power of God, no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113795:22"/> reaſon can be given; why, for example, it ſhould be more ſtrange or incredible, that men (as by ancient Heathens, as well Philoſophers, as others, they were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally conceived to have begun at the firſt) ſhould ſpring out of the earth, as plants and trees; then to be propagated, as they are, by way of generation; in the right and rationall conſideration whereof ſo many particulars, ſo wonderfull and ſo incomprehenſible to humane reaſon, offer themſelves, that the ableſt Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts the world hath had, as well Heathens, as others, have freely acknowledged their ignorance, and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of underſtanding, and have been excited (ſome of them) to praiſe and glorifie God for his wonderfull works, as <hi>Galen</hi> doth in divers of his writings, upon this occaſion. And certainly had it been ſo, that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way of propagation (as it is conceived by divers An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, that another way would have been, if man had not ſinned) had been eſtabliſhed by God; I am of <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> his opinion, that this way, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.) if then propoſed to any mans conſideration, would have ſeemed as incredible and impoſſible, as whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, in that kind, is propoſed to our beleef as Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Hence it is that the Apoſtle where he diſcourſeth of the reſurrection of the dead, (at the poſſibility of which ſo many ſtumbled) he appeals to approved ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of things naturall, <hi>Thou foole,</hi> ſaith he,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.36, 37, 38.</note> 
                  <hi>that which thou ſoweſt is not quickned except it die. And that which thou ſoweſt, thou ſoweſt not that body that ſhall be, but bare grain, it may be of wheat, or of ſome other grain. But God giveth it a body, as it hath pleaſed him, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſeed his own body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But this myſtery of Chriſt, the Eternall Son of God,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113795:23"/> his Incarnation, is quite of another nature. That which in other things doth, or may ſatisfie a rationall man, here it encreaſeth the wonder, and makes it more incredible. <hi>Ye doe erre,</hi> ſaith Chriſt to ſome that could not beleeve the reſurrection of the dead,<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 22.29.</note> 
                  <hi>not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God.</hi> But here the more <hi>we know the power of God,</hi> the fuller and perfecter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion we have of his Greatneſſe, &amp; Omnipotency, the more incredible may this myſtery ſeem unto us. Holy <hi>David</hi> in the 143. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> but upon occaſion of a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall deliverance, <hi>the hurtfull ſword,</hi> in the 9. verſe) with admiration fals into this conſideration, <hi>Lord what is man that thou takeſt knowledge of him, or the ſon of man, that thou makeſt account of him?</hi> And in another place, the conſideration of the world, and works of God, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed this ſweete and devout ejaculation from him,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. taken in the literall ſenſe: for in the myſticall ſenſe, theſe very words are applied to this myſtery, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</note> 
                  <hi>When I conſider the Heavens, the Moon and the Stars which thou haſt ordained: What is man that thou art mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of him; and the ſon of man that thou viſiteſt him?</hi> But Lord, may we ſay, Thou, <hi>Who covereſt thy ſelf with light as with a garment: who ſtretcheſt out the Heavens like a Curtain: Who laidſt the beams of thy chambers in the waters; who makeſt the clouds thy charet; who walkeſt upon the wings of the wind. Who haſt meaſured the waters in the hollow of thy hand; and meted out Heaven with thy ſpan; Before whom all nations are as nothing;</hi> yea, <hi>leſſe then nothing and vanity:</hi> Thou, who ſaidſt, <hi>Let there be light, and there was light:</hi> Let the <hi>Firmament</hi> appear, and it did appear; the <hi>waters flow,</hi> and they did <hi>flow:</hi> Who as thou didſt at the firſt make Heaven and Earth, and all that in them is, with a word of thy mouth; ſo canſt with the leaſt blaſt reduce them all
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113795:23"/> to their firſt <hi>Chaos</hi> and nothing: <hi>What is man,</hi> that for his ſake thou wouldſt <hi>be made man:</hi> that ever, for man's ſake, it ſhould be ſaid of thee, <hi>Hee hath no forme nor comelineſſe: He is deſpiſed and rejected of men:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 53.3, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>a man of ſorrows, and acquainted with grief:</hi> or ever Thou ſhouldſt have occaſion to ſay of thy ſelf;<note place="margin">Mat. 8.20.</note> 
                  <hi>The Foxes have holes, and the birds of the aire have neſts: but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I wonder not if the Prophet ſay, <hi>Who hath belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved our report?</hi> never had infidelity (were it not for divine revelation) a more plauſible colour. Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome inferre wittily, that the incredibility of this myſtery ſhould (if rightly conſidered) make it the more credible. For, ſay they,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theod. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rap. l. 6.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>&amp;c. Salv. De Gubern. Dei lib. 4.</hi> Vtique hoc ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis maeſtimabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis pietas, &amp;c. <hi>Sed omnium acutiſſimè Tertul.</hi> De Bapt. c. <hi>2.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui eò magis credendum, ſi quia mirandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, idcircò non credendum. Qualia enim decet eſſe opera divina, niſi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra omnem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirationem? <hi>1 Joh. 4.8, 9.</hi>
                  </note> ſuch goodneſſe doth beſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come an infinite Omnipotent God, ſo great and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive, as for the very greatneſſe, it ſhould not ſeem credible. But to this muſt be added, (to make the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation more ſolid) that as God is infinite in all that he is; ſo more particularly and peculiarly, in love and goodneſſe: becauſe love and goodneſſe, (if there be any impropriety in the ſpeech, it muſt be excuſed, becauſe we cannot otherwiſe ſpeak of God, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly) are his very nature and eſſence. As ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cination, (ſay the Schoolmen) is the proper nature of man, <hi>ſic ipſa natura Dei eſt eſſentia bonitatis.</hi> For which they refer us, to their ſuppoſed <hi>Dionyſius Areopagita:</hi> But why not rather to Saint <hi>John?</hi> Doth not Saint <hi>John</hi> upon this very occaſion of Chriſt his Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion poſitively ſay, that (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>God is love? He that loveth not,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>knoweth not God; For God is love. In this was manifeſted the love of God towards us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that God ſent his onely begotten Son into the world,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113795:24"/> that wee might live through him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the love of men towards their own children, what admirable effects and operations upon extraordinary emergent occaſions it hath had in divers, much might be ſaid out of ancient and later ſtories: much more, and more wonderfull, (becauſe grounded upon na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture onely; whereas that of man, upon reaſon and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety alſo) of the love of dumb creatures towards their young ones; whereof Poets, and Naturaliſts that have written of their nature, treat at large, and give many inſtances. Now upon this, <hi>Salvian</hi> (an ancient Father, <hi>Presbyter Maſsilienſis,</hi> by his title; but ſtyled by <hi>Genna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius, Epiſcoporum Magiſter</hi>) inferreth thus: (it is upon another occaſion, Gods Providence; but it is applied by himſelf to this ſubject of Chriſt his Incarnation) <hi>Deus ergò qui etiam minimis animantibus, &amp;c.</hi> that is, <hi>God therefore who even in the leaſt creatures,</hi> (as <hi>Ants</hi> and <hi>Bees,</hi> ſpoken of before) <hi>hath planted this affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their own, how can it be that he ſhould bereave him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of it? Eſpecially, when all love of good things in us, proceedeth from his good love. For he is the ſource and fountain of all things: and becauſe in him</hi> (as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) <hi>we live, move, and have our beeing; from him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have derived this affection, whereby we embrace thoſe that are our own. For all the world, and all mankind,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Pignus eſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atoris ſui.</note> 
                  <hi>are reſemblances,</hi> (or <hi>evidences) of their Creator. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by this affection wherewith we embrace</hi> (pignora no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra) <hi>thoſe that are our own; he would have us to know how much he loveth</hi> (pignora ſua) <hi>thoſe that proceed from him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a myſtery therefore of this nature, ſo far excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the capacity of man, as that the weakeſt and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113795:24"/> of men, beyond what is revealed by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, are as the talleſt and loweſt ſtatures to the height of the higheſt heavens; and again, a myſtery of ſo much importance to us, ſo much partly by profeſſed Infidels openly contradicted and oppoſed; and partly by cunning Hereticks ſophiſticated and depraved; it doth much concern every ſyncere Chriſtian to be well furniſhed and provided of ſuch principall clear texts of Scripture, as the wiſdome of God hath provided unto us to that end; not ſo much to ſatisfie our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, as to ſettle our faith and our beleefe. Three ſpeciall branches of this great myſtery there be, about which the curioſity and infidelity of men hath eſpecially ſtumbled, and wherein it doth mainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern all true Chriſtians to be well grounded: which are, 1. The Deity; 2. The Humanity (two natures in one Perſon) of Chriſt; and 3. The Merit and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation of his bloud. Concerning theſe, taking them ſeverally in the order by us propoſed, wee conceive theſe places of Scripture, taken in themſelves with that light onely which being thus joyned and put together, they do afford and hold forth to one another, without any further gloſſe or comment, to be very full, preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and ſatisfactory.</p>
               <p>Firſt, concerning the Deity of Chriſt, theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:
<q>
                     <p>Behold, a Virgin ſhall be with childe,<note place="margin">Matth. 1.23.</note> and ſhall bring forth a Son, and they ſhall call his name Emmanuel, which being interpreted is, God with us.</p>
                     <p>In the beginning was the Word,<note place="margin">Joh. 1.1, 2, 3, 4.</note> and the Word was with God, and the Word was God. The ſame was in the beginning
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113795:25"/> with God. All things were made by him, and without him was not any thing made that was made. In him was life, and the life was the light of man.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">John 5.18.</note>Therefore the Jews ſought the more to kill him, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe he had broken the Sabbath, but ſaid alſo that God was his Father, making himſelf equall with God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 9.5.</note>Whoſe are the Fathers, &amp; of whom as concerning the fleſh, Chriſt came, who is over all, God bleſſed for ever. Amen.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Philip. 2.6.</note>Who being in the forme of God, thought it no robbery to be equall with God.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note>And without controverſie, great is the myſtery of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: God manifeſt in the fleſh, &amp;c. Looking for the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed hope, and the glorious appearing of the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt: Who gave himſelf for us, &amp;c.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, concerning his humanity, or humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, theſe:
<q>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">John 1.14.</note>And the Word was made fleſh, and dwelt among us, (and we beheld his glory, the glory as of the onely begotten of the Father) full of grace and truth.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Rom. 1.3.</note>Concerning his Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, which was made of the ſeed of <hi>David</hi> according to the fleſh.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Gal. 4.4.</note>But when the fulneſſe of the time was come, God ſent forth his Son, made of a woman, made under the Law.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.5.</note>For there is one God, and one Mediator between God and man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Heb. 2.14.</note>For as much then as the children are partakers of fleſh and bloud, he alſo himſelf likewiſe took part of the ſame, that through death he might deſtroy him that had the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of death; that is, the Devill.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Heb. 2.16, 17.</note>For verily he tooke not on him the nature of Angels, but he took on him the ſeed of <hi>Abraham.</hi> Wherefore in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113795:25"/> all things it behoved him to bee made like unto his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Hereby know ye the Spirit of God:<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.2, 3.</note> Every ſpirit that confeſſeth that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh, is of God. And every ſpirit that confeſſeth not, &amp;c.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, that Chriſt offer'd himſelf as a Propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for our ſins, theſe:</p>
               <q>
                  <p>Even as the Son of man came not to be miniſtred unto,<note place="margin">Matth. 20.28.</note> but to miniſter, and to give his life a ranſome for many.</p>
                  <p>The next day <hi>John</hi> ſeeth Jeſus comming unto him,<note place="margin">John 1.29.</note> and ſaith, Behold the Lamb of God, which taketh away the ſin of the world.</p>
                  <p>For God ſo loved the world,<note place="margin">3.16.</note> that he gave his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son, that whoſoever beleeveth in him ſhould not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, but have everlaſting life.</p>
                  <p>Take heed therefore unto your ſelves, and to all the flock,<note place="margin">Acts 20.28.</note> over the which the holy Ghoſt hath made you overſeers, to feed the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own blood.</p>
                  <p>Being juſtified freely by his grace,<note place="margin">Rom. 3.24.5.</note> through the redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that is in Jeſus Chriſt: Whom God hath ſet forth to be a propitiation, through faith in his bloud, to declare his righteouſneſſe, for the remiſsi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n of ſins that are paſt, through the forbearanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of God.</p>
                  <p>But of him are ye in Chriſt Jeſus,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.30.</note> who of God is made un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us Wiſdome, and Righteouſneſſe, and Sanctification, and Redemption.</p>
                  <p>But Chriſt being come an high Prieſt of good things to come, &amp;c neither by the bloud of goats and calves;<note place="margin">Heb. 9.11, 12, 13, 14.</note> but by his own bloud he entred in once into the holy place, having obtained eternall redemption for us. For if the bloud of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:113795:26"/> buls and goats, and the aſhes of an heifer ſprinkling the unclean, ſanctifieth to the purifying of the fleſh: How much more ſhall the bloud of Chriſt, who through the eternall Spirit offered himſel without ſpot to God, purge your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience from dead works, to ſerve the living God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 9.26.</note>For then, &amp;c. but now once in the end of the world hath he appeared to put away ſin by the ſacrifice of himſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.24.</note>Who his own ſelf bare our ſins in his own body on the tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, that we beeng dead to ſins, ſhould live unto righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; by whoſe ſtripes ye were healed.</p>
               </q>
               <p>I ſaid before, my purpoſe was not to encounter ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries here, but to comfort and confirm them who ſtood unſhaken in the <hi>ſame precious faith,</hi> (to uſe Saint <hi>Peters</hi> words) upon which precious faith the Church was firſt founded, and which by the ſucceſſion of ſo many ages hath been continued and derived unto us. Otherwiſe we might and muſt have taken notice of many more places; and not content our ſelves with paſſages and teſtimonies of the New Teſtament only, but ground eſpecially upon propheſies of the Old: as alſo have taken notice of many falſe gloſſes &amp; interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, whereby the adverſaries have endeavoured to elude the cleareſt teſtimonies of either; whether Old or New Teſtament: all which could not be without much more diſcourſe, then I can allow my ſelfe at this time. Of propheſies, there is not any that hath either more troubled the obſtinate Jews; (as appears by their writings) or converted more of the more candid and ingenuous among them, then the fifty third Chapter of the Prophet <hi>Eſay:</hi> which whole Chapter both as a precious cordiall to them that are
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113795:26"/> wounded in ſpirit; and an excellent antidote againſt the danger of all ſpreading infection of unſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in this main fundamentall, deſerves to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to memory; or at leaſt often to be read and pondered by all prudent and wary Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>There be ſome texts of Scripture concerning this high and ſublime myſtery, which by them that are not well grounded, without ſome precaution, may eaſily be miſtaken. We are taught by the Scriptures and true analogy of faith, that the Word is ſo united unto our fleſh, the nature of God unto the nature of man, as that both make but one perſon: though but one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, yet ſo nevertheleſſe, that as the natures themſelves, ſo the properties of both, remain, diſtinct, unpermixed, unconfuſed. But this though in the truth and reality of the thing it bee perpetuall and immutable, yet in verball expreſſions it is not ſo preciſely obſerved. There is a <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. (as they commonly call it) that is, <hi>a communication of idioms and properties,</hi> in words and ſpeeches, ſometimes uſed. Ancient Fathers call it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, (or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) a <hi>communication</hi> not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>of properties;</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>of names or words.</hi> S. <hi>Cyrill</hi> uſeth the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>appropriation;</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcen</hi> (beſides other words, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and the like) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, about the right interpretation of which word there is ſome controverſie amongſt the Learned. Theſe kinde of expreſſions, however called, have bred great diſputes and occaſioned (as much as any thing) that dolefull diviſion between us, and thoſe Proteſtants commonly called <hi>Lutherans,</hi> they contending, that this communication of properties is not <hi>verball</hi> onely, but <hi>reall:</hi> whereupon they inferre ſtrange concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113795:27"/> The truth is, as ſome moderate learned men (of this ſide eſpecially) ſtate the buſineſſe, the controverſie it ſelf may ſeem rather verball, then reall: not ſuch at leaſt, as ſhould diſturb the peace of the Church, ſo much as it hath done. But we will not meddle with controverſies. For the better underſtanding of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in this ſacred ſubject, I finde five rules, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions collected out of them: or rather the ſeverall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, and <hi>modos loquendi</hi> there uſed upon this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, digeſted and reduced into five heads, or rules. They are ſuch as every body needs not, I know; but ſuch as every body is very well capable of, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhall the more willingly inſert them here.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>I.</abbr>
                  </note>The firſt is, ſome things are ſpoken of Chriſt in the Scriptures, which muſt be underſtood of his divine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture onely; as, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.5. <hi>Chriſt, who is over us all, God bleſſed for ever.</hi> John 8.58. <hi>Before</hi> Abraham <hi>was, I am.</hi> Heb. 1.2, 3. <hi>By whom alſo he made the worlds. Who being the brightneſſe of his glory, and the expreſſe image of his Perſon, and upholding all things by the word of his power:</hi> and other like places.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>II.</abbr>
                  </note>The ſecond is, Some things are ſpoken of Chriſt, which muſt be underſtood of his humane nature onely; as, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.31. <hi>Thou ſhalt conceive in thy womb, and bring forth a Son, and ſhalt call his Name Jeſus.</hi> Luke 2.52. <hi>And Jeſus increaſed in wiſdome and ſtature, and in favour with God and man.</hi> Matth. 26 39. <hi>Nevertheleſſe, not as I will, but as thou wilt;</hi> and the like.</p>
               <p>Some, at firſt hearing, may think that thoſe ſpeeches, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20.23. <hi>(But to ſit on my right hand and on my left, is not mine to give; but it ſhall be given to them, for whom it is prepared of my Father)</hi> and <hi>Mark</hi> 13.32. <hi>(But of that
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113795:27"/> day and that houre knoweth no man, no not the Angels which are in heaven, neither the Son, but the Father)</hi> ſhould bee referred to this head or rule. Certain enough it is that of the Ancients not a few did ſo underſtand them as ſpoken by Chriſt of himſelf, not as God, but Man. But moſt Interpreters expound them otherwiſe, and ſhew reaſons why that expoſition, as contrary to other places of Scripture, cannot ſtand. The truth is, they are diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces, as may appear by the diverſity of expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. But I will not make it my buſineſſe here. This ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veat I thought would not be amiſſe, which is all I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
               <p>The third is, ſome things are ſpoken of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                     <abbr>III.</abbr>
                  </note> which muſt be underſtood of his Perſon onely, not of either of his natures particularly; as, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.5. <hi>This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed; hear ye him.</hi> Eph. 5.23. <hi>Chriſt is the head of the Church, and he is the Saviour of the body.</hi> 1 Tim. 2.5, 6. <hi>One Mediator between God and man, the Man Chriſt Jeſus. Who gave himſelf a ranſome for all, to be teſtified in due time:</hi> and the like. To this head are referred all ſuch as concern Chriſt his Office. For Chriſt is not our Mediator, but as he is both God and Man. It were groſſe blaſphemy to ſay, (in property of ſpeech) that the divine nature of Chriſt did ſuffer; but that he ſuffered as God and Man, we muſt beleeve; the conſideration of his divinity concurring with the ſufferings of his humane nature, to make them availa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>The fourth is,<note place="margin">
                     <abbr>IV.</abbr>
                  </note> Some things are ſpoken of Chriſt as God, which muſt be underſtood of his humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture onely; as, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.8. <hi>For had they known it, they would not have crucified the Lord of Glory.</hi> Acts 20.28.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113795:28"/> 
                  <hi>Feed the Church of God, which he hath purchaſed with his own bloud.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <abbr>V.</abbr>
                  </note>The fifth is, Some things are ſpoken of Chriſt as Man, which muſt be underſtood of his divine nature; as, <hi>John</hi> 3.13. <hi>No man hath aſcended up to Heaven, but he that came down from Heaven: even the Sonne of Man which is in Heaven.</hi> Matth. 9.6. <hi>But that ye may know that the Son of Man hath power on earth to forgive ſins, &amp;c.</hi> Joh. 6.62 <hi>What and if ye ſhall ſee the Son of Man aſcend up where he was before?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is ſome difference between us and the <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans</hi> whether in theſe paſſages of the two laſt rules, (the 4. and the 5.) the <hi>idiomata,</hi> or properties of one nature ſhould be ſaid to be communicated to the other nature; or rather (as we maintain) to the Perſon. The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of this difference, if neerly ſifted, may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what; but otherwiſe (we acknowledging the reality of this communication of idiomes, in the Perſon; and they ſo bounding and expounding that communication which they maintain, as that the properties of both na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures may ſtill continue really diſtinct) there appears to me but little neceſſity of ſuch quarrelling about it.</p>
               <p>To theſe rules of diſtinctions, the Scripture it ſelfe in direct tearms, or by formall precedents doth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time lead us: as S. <hi>Peter</hi> in thoſe words, (ſpeaking of Chriſt) <hi>being put to death in the fleſh</hi> (1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.18.) and <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for us in the fleſh: (Ibid.</hi> 4.1.) and the ſame <hi>Peter,</hi> Chapter 2.23. <hi>Who his own ſelf bare our ſins in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> (not, <hi>in corpore proprio,</hi> or, <hi>ſuo ipſius;</hi> but, <hi>in corpore ſuo,</hi> as both <hi>Beza,</hi> and the Vulgar; which I conceive more proper, though it be in the Originall, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>on the tree.</hi> So S. <hi>Paul, Which was made of the ſeeed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113795:28"/> of</hi> David, <hi>according to the fleſh,</hi> Rom. 1.3. and Chap. 9.3. to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>Of whom, as concerning the fleſh, Chriſt came.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I finde that moſt who have written of this ſubject, both Schoolmen and others, take into conſideration the neceſſity of Chriſt his Incarnation, or as ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it, of his ſatisfaction, for the reparation of mankind: Some alſo inſiſt much upon it, as a main circumſtance. This puts a neceſſity upon me, of ſaying ſomewhat of it, who otherwiſe could have reſted well ſatisfied in the ſimple knowledge of that way of ſalvation, which the wiſdome of God hath pitched upon, with thoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations which himſelf in his holy Word, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended it unto us with, without going ſo high, as the conſideration of the poſſibility of another way.</p>
               <p>But ſince I may not altogether omit it, my firſt care ſhall be rightly to ſtate the queſtion; which is not, Whether the reparation of mankind, and thereupon the Incarnation of Chriſt was abſolutely neceſſary: that Chriſt would have been incarnated, though man had not ſinned, hath been, I know, the opinion of ſome; but that the reparation of man being falne, was abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, not of any, that I remember: Neither is this the queſtion, Whether upon a ſuppoſition, that ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction muſt be had, any other true and proper ſatifacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on could be found, but in, and by Chriſt; which is a point handled by<note n="a" place="margin">Vide Chryſoſt. Theodoret &amp;c. in <hi>1</hi> Tim. <hi>2.5.</hi> Sed praecipuè Athan. Orat. <hi>2. cont. Arr.</hi> &amp; Cyrill. Alexan. <hi>De rectâ fide, ad Theodoſ. &amp; R ginas.</hi>
                  </note> divers of the Ancients, who give ſundry reaſons grounded upon the Scripture, that it could not; and hath<note n="b" place="margin">Vid. Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſ. Archiep. Armachanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctatum qui inſcribitur <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> vel, <hi>De myſterio Incarn.</hi>
                  </note> lately by ſome of eminent worth and ranke, more accurately been diſcuſſed and proved: but, this ſuppoſed, that God after the fall of <hi>Adam</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a purpoſe to reſtore mankind to its former, or a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:113795:29"/> better ſtate both of innocency and felicity, whether he might not have brought it about any other way then by the Incarnation of his Son: or thus, (for it comes all to one, and ſo it is propoſed by ſome) Whether God can forgive ſins without a proportionable ſatisfaction; this is the queſtion intended hereby us.</p>
               <p>This ſpeculation was firſt occaſioned by the objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and ſcruples of ancient Heathens, who as they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked well to heare of Gods mercy in generall, ſo they could not (many of them) digeſt, that the Almighty ſhould be put to ſuch ſhifts, and ſtoop ſo low, (as they interpreted it) for the execution of it. Moſt ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Writers, that I have obſerved, reſolve the queſtion affirmatively, that it was very poſſible to God, either ſome other way; or without any at all, by his bare will and pleaſure. So, not <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> onely, who are cited by learned <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> in his Treatiſe <hi>De Satisfactione;</hi> but S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> alſo, (or who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is the Author of that excellent piece <hi>De cardinali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus operibus Chriſti) Origen, Theodoret; Leo,</hi> and <hi>Gregory,</hi> two Popes, for their ſingular worth and piety, ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Great.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Theod. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rap. l. 6.</note>
                  <hi>Theodoret</hi> having firſt ſhewed how many things God had made for mans ſake, and thereupon inferred how well it became him to reſtore them being faln, for whom ſuch ſtore and plenty, in Heaven and in Earth, was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and provided; and ſo proceeded in his diſcourſe to the Incarnation of Chriſt, goes on thus: <hi>It was very eaſie for him without this veyling of himſelf with our fleſh to have wrought this ſalvation of mankind, and by his bare will not onely to have deſtroyed the power of death; but ſin alſo,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>the mother of death; and the begetter
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:113795:29"/> of ſin, that miſchievous ſpirit; the one to have altogether aboliſhed; and the other, to have driven from the earth, and confined to his after a ſhort ſeaſon appointed habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, [eternall] darkneſſe.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pariter &amp; Leo, 2. De Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivit.</hi> Miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia Dei, cum ad recuperandu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> genus humanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ineffabiliter ei multa ſuppete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, hanc po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimum conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendi viam ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>git, quâ ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruendum opus Diaboli, non virtute utere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur potentiae, ſed ratione ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiae.</note> 
                  <hi>But it was not the will of God in this to manifeſt his abſolute power; but the juſtice and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his providence,</hi> (or, <hi>wiſdome.</hi>)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen,</hi> (whom I mention for his antiquity, though not always to be followed in his opinions) upon this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, becauſe the queſtion propoſed by <hi>Celſus</hi> the Heathen was not, whether any other way in generall; but particularly, why not ſuch a way rather; he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents himſelf to ſhew the impertinency of the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and that the way by <hi>Celſus</hi> propoſed, was not ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Providence of God, or to the nature of man, ſo ſutable and convenient: but of the poſſibility in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, as he doth not deny it, ſo neither doth he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptorily affirm it. He doth not; (not there at leaſt) but others doe; and their determination of the matter is embraced by the Schoolmen, <hi>Peter Lombard,</hi> and <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Aquinas,</hi> and others: by Proteſtants alſo, <hi>Zanchius, Polanus, Peter Martyr, Paraeus:</hi> and many more, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve. <hi>Gerardus,</hi> and moſt of the <hi>Lutheran</hi> party, hold the contrary opinion; and not they onely, but of our ſide alſo ſome not of the obſcureſt.</p>
               <p>For my part, in reverence to God and his truth free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to deliver my minde, leaving others to the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their own judgements, I muſt profeſſe that I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſatisfie my ſelf, how it can ſtand with the duty and humility of mortall men, who can give ſo little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our ſelves, (either of our ſouls or bodies) to attempt the ſounding of ſuch an abyſſus, ſuch a bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe Ocean, as either the Power or the Mercy of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:113795:30"/> Almighty God and out of phyſicall<note n="*" place="margin">Vide Teſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum <hi>De Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra &amp; Gratiâ:</hi> &amp; nuperas (ut alios praeterea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) Joh. Hoornbeck <hi>Diſputationes Antijudaicas.</hi>
                  </note> or metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall ſpeculations (for ſuch I account all in this kinde, that are not apparently grounded upon divine autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity) ſo peremptorily and poſitively to determine how farre either can goe. I tremble to think what hapned to the <hi>Bethſhemites,</hi> for offering to pry into the Ark, the Mercy-ſeat of God. Of all things in the world, I would not abridge the Power of God in point of Mercy, whereof there is ſo much need in the world. If God himſelf doth limit, I adore his judgements, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit with all humility. Where he doth not, I will not certainly: no authority of mortall man, no ſubtilty of humane wit ſhall perſwade me to do it. Earthly Kings and Princes will not endure their Prerogative ſhould be ſcanned by every Subject; not by any perchance, if they could help it: and good Kings will eſteeme mercy the beſt part of their Prerogative. Owe wee not then ſo much reſpect to the King of Kings, the Omnipotent Creator of all things, who from his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Throne beholdeth the Inhabitants of the earth (Kings and Monarchs, as well as others) as ſo many worms or graſhoppers, as to leave him the power and Prerogative of his Mercy indiſputed; free and unboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? That any who was not a God, ſhould take upon him to forgive ſins, was once we know thought blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy: (<hi>Mark</hi> 2.7.) how ſhall it not be ſome ſpice of blaſphemy, to bereave God of this power, except God himſelf in his revealed Word doth expreſly diſclaim it?</p>
               <p>We ſee in the Goſpel, when the Diſciples upon the words of their Maſter, that it <hi>is eaſier for a camel to goe through the eye of a needle, then for a rich man to enter
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:113795:30"/> into the Kingdome of God,</hi> began to infer (as probably enough they might) that none therefore, or very few, (for ſo muſt their words, not pertinent otherwiſe, be underſtood: moſt men being either rich, or covetouſly ſeeking after riches; which comes all to one) could be ſaved; Chriſt himſelf teacheth them in ſuch caſes, not to judge raſhly, but to remember the power of God: <hi>With men,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>this is unpoſsible; but with God all things are poſsible.</hi> By which words Chriſt ſeemeth in ſome manner to juſtifie their inference in point of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ratiocination; (for that men cannot ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves or be ſaved by other men, whereof no queſtion was made, is not it that Chriſt acknowledges here im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible with men) but to diſallow of humane ratioci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation in things of this nature.</p>
               <p>But now on the other ſide, if any pretend Scripture (as moſt doe) for their opinion, I anſwer; If clear Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, (as in ſuch points would be requiſite) how come ſo many, both ancient and late, ſo well verſed in them, ſo able to judge of them, to be of another opinion? If doubtfull and diſputable, then in ſuch a caſe that comes ſo neer to blaſphemy, (without good warrant from God himſelf) I hold the affirmative, as more plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſo ſafer every way.</p>
               <p>To paſſe by therefore their arguments which are drawn, as was ſaid before, moſt of them from meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicall ſpeculations, which I deſire not to meddle with; I will onely take notice of ſome conſiderations inſiſted upon by ſome of them to make their opinion more plauſible, if not neceſſary.</p>
               <p>The firſt is, that to beleeve the poſſibility of mans reſtauration, either without any ſatisfaction at all, (by
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:113795:31"/> free pardon) or any other way of ſatisfaction, (if any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way can be, which as we ſaid before, we doe not conceive) is to undervalue the benefit and high price of this holy <hi>Diſpenſation.</hi> It is certain, the apprehenſions of men, though their end, to glorifie God, be the ſame, may be different; and a difference of apprehenſions may make a difference of opinions, though tending to one end. I join with them therefore in their main drift; but I doe not conceive that any man who really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeves an impoſſibility (grounded upon Gods revealed Word) of any mans ſalvation without Chriſt, needs any other motive to induce him to ſet a right price up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this miraculous work, then the conſideration of his own, and every mans happineſſe thereon depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
               <p>It is, ſecondly, further objected, that this opinion may ſeem to ſavour, or at leaſt, to favour <hi>Sociniſme;</hi> who ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly plead againſt the neceſſity, &amp; make it an argument againſt the truth of Chriſt his ſatisfaction. But ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the way to deal with <hi>Socinians,</hi> is not by ſuch rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning. God be praiſed, we have a more ſure way, and that is the way of divine authority. If that doe it not, it is to be feared, weaker proofs, which not without much probability may bee contradicted, will rather confirm them, then convert them. What Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi> ſaith in a place upon another occaſion, would be conſidered upon this, <hi>Metus eſt ne cum ſaepe ſubruun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>De Magiſtro.</hi> quod totidem ſere verbis etiam Plato non un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> loco.</note> 
                  <hi>quae firmiſſimè ſtatura et manſura praeſumimus, in tantum odium vel timorem rationis incidamus, ut ne ipſi quidem perſpicuae veritati fides habenda videatur;</hi> that is, <hi>It is to bee feared, that when men ſhall ſee thoſe reaſons, which they once grounded upon as firm and ſtable, eaſily
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:113795:31"/> and familiarly overthrown, they fall at laſt into ſuch a hatred or ſuſpition of reaſon, that even the moſt undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted truths ſhall not be beleeved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am therefore much pleaſed with <hi>Balth. Meiſnerus</hi> (a <hi>Lutheran</hi>) his prudent moderation in this point, who in his Diſputations againſt the <hi>Socinians,</hi> upon ſuch grounds of reaſon as are ordinarily inſiſted upon by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, having ſaid as much as can with any colour be ſaid for this neceſſity,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Balth. Meiſne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> A <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Dec. 3. Diſp. 26.90.</note> concludes his <hi>Diſputation</hi> in theſe words: [<hi>Hitherto, why God could not without ſome preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice to his Omnipotency pardon ſinners without ſome ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, hath been ſhewed. But that we ſhould enter into this diſpute with our adverſaries, is not ſo abſolutely neceſſary; becauſe thereby we are forced to enquire into the reaſons of the divine counſell, which ought not to be. Gods revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his divine will by his Word ought to ſuffice us, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he declareth, that without the price and merit of his Son, as a Mediator, he will not forgive ſin, becauſe he hateth it, and for it, is angry with ſinners. That it is ſo, therefore let us beleeve, and that</hi> [by this kind of ſatisfaction] <hi>the divine Omnipotency is no ways impaired, becauſe both thoſe are affirmed by the Scriptures, though we cannot render a reaſon of all the counſels of God. Theſe things ought rather to be admired, and with thankfull hearts extolled, then with niceneſſe and curioſity ſifted and diſcuſſed.</hi>] He repeates the ſame, though in other words, as fully in the 105. Paragraph of the ſame <hi>Diſputation.</hi> And in the 89. commends this Canon: <hi>Quid Deus circa ſalutem no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram faciat, non ex rationibus de poſſibili colligendum, ſed ex ſolis Scripturis addiſcendum eſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But doth not the Scripture plainly fay, (I take notice of this objection, becauſe the phraſe doth often occur,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:113795:32"/> &amp; may trouble them that are not ſo expert) that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebat:</hi> Chriſt ought to ſuffer ſuch &amp; ſuch things? Are not Chriſt his own words, <hi>John</hi> 3.14. <hi>As</hi> Moſes <hi>lifted up the Serpent in the Wilderneſſe, even ſo muſt the Son of man be lifted up;</hi> Muſt? yes, it is the Scripture phraſe, but more full in other places; as <hi>Luke</hi> 24.44. <hi>Theſe are the words which I ſpake to you, while I was yet with you, that all things muſt be fulfilled which were written in the Law of</hi> Moſes, <hi>and in the Prophets, and in the Pſalms concerning me.</hi> And again in the next words, <hi>Then opened he their underſtanding, that they might underſtand the Scriptures, And ſaid unto them, Thus it is written, and thus it behoved</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſame word as before) <hi>Chriſt to ſuffer, and to riſe the third day from the dead.</hi> By which and other like places it doth clearly appear, that this <hi>muſt,</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation meerly to the predictions of the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment concerning Chriſt, whether by words; or, (as that of the Serpent lifted up in the Wilderneſſe) by types. God therefore having long before not onely preordained, but alſo by ſeverall Prophets foretold the ſufferings of Chriſt, it was not onely expedient, but (in this reſpect) abſolutely neceſſary, that all things ſhould fall out accordingly; For <hi>It is eaſier that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth ſhould paſſe, then one tittle of the Law to fail,</hi> Luk 16.17. Now that which made Chriſt ſo often to preſſe the Scripture to the Jewes, was to convince them by their own principles, that whereas they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed much zeal for the Scriptures, they might know that thoſe very Scriptures, which they were ſo zealous for, were the very ground (in ſome ſenſe) both of his doctrine, and of all that hapned unto him. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, to conſider the things in the order of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:113795:32"/> thoſe things did not (ſo properly) happen to Chriſt, becauſe they were foretold; but becauſe they were ſo determined by God from all eternity, therefore they were firſt foretold, and afterwards hapned according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Act.</hi> 4.28.</p>
               <p>Laying therefore aſide this abſolute neceſſity, as not grounded (for ought we could ever finde) upon any Scriptures, and as we conceive of dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence; we may with leſſe danger, and no leſſe edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, we hope, take notice of ſuch reaſons or conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, as the wit of man can reach unto, by which this counſell of God (<hi>Diſpenſation</hi> or <hi>Oeconomy</hi> the Ancients uſually call it) in a rationall triall, if need be, may be maintained <hi>convenient</hi> or <hi>plauſible;</hi> though in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed moſt of theſe conſiderations be grounded upon Scripture, as will appear. But they muſt firſt be fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warned that are not ſo throughly acquainted with the tearms belonging to this ſubject, that in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular conſideration of the neceſſity or expedience of Chriſt's Incarnation; in the word <hi>Incarnation</hi> (as often beſides) is preſuppoſed to be included the Paſſion alſo, as the principall end of it: according to that of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 12.27. <hi>Father, ſave me from this houre: but for this cauſe came I, unto this houre.</hi> For ſo I conceive the words ſhould be diſtinguiſhed, and interpreted, <hi>But for this cauſe came I;</hi> (into the world, that is, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>This is a faithfull ſaying and worthy of all acceptation, that Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15.) <hi>unto this houre;</hi> that is, that I might ſuffer for ſinners.</p>
               <p>The firſt and chiefeſt reaſon will be, that God choſe this way, as the moſt convenient to manifeſt his love
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:113795:33"/> to mankind: according to that of Chriſt in S. <hi>John, So God loved the world, that he gave his onely begotten Sonne, that whoſoever beleeveth in him ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life.</hi> This conſideration is not onely men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned often in the Scripture, but alſo ſet forth &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended unto us by ſeverall circumſtances, all very conſiderable to make us the more apprehenſive of it. See <hi>John</hi> 15.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.6, 7, 8. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4 9, 10. Now of this manifeſtation of his love in ſuch an extraordinary way one main end was, the more powerfully to draw ours to himſelf, and to withdraw it from the love of the world: which two are inconſiſtent. See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14, 15. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.4. <hi>John</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 2.15, 16, 17. This is the main conſideration that hath made ſo many Martyrs.</p>
               <p>A ſecond conſideration might be, the better to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt his juſtice, and his extream antipathy (if we may ſo ſpeak) to ſin: thereby alſo (from the conſideration of this antipathy in God) the more powerfully to draw us to the love of goodneſſe and vertue; and to a true hearty deteſtation of wickedneſſe. Whence, as I take it, eſpecially it is, that according to the Scripture phraſe, all impenitent ſinners, who profeſſe godlineſſe, but ſhew not the power of it in their lives and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, are ſtyled <hi>Infidels,</hi> or <hi>unbeleevers,</hi> as being alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether impoſſible, that they that truly beleeve, or have a true apprehenſion of this <hi>great myſtery of godlineſſe,</hi> ſhould continue in ungodlineſſe.</p>
               <p>A third conſideration was certainly, that Chriſt might by his example work upon us the more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually to imitate him, as in other things, ſo eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in his <hi>humilitie,</hi> the moſt proper vertue of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and without which all profeſſion of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:113795:33"/> is but deluſion and impoſture. But of this more in its proper place afterwards, in the conſideration of his <hi>Exinanition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To theſe, divers others might be added, but either not ſo pertinent, or ſuch as might be reduced to theſe. Even of theſe that we have ſet down, if a man be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to multiply queſtions, it may be asked, whether by ſome other cauſe, or way, ſuch ends and ſuch ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects might not have been contrived and compaſſed. There is no end of ſuch curioſity; but as no end, ſo as little fruit.</p>
               <p>There is nothing among men ſo generally recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or approved in the ways and works of God, but ſuch as are bold, and ſelf-conceited, may eaſily except againſt, and think they might have mended it, if they had had the ordering of it. So that in the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we muſt either ſink our ſelves into Atheiſm (then which in other reſpects and conſiderations, nothing can be more contrary to ſenſe and reaſon) or be forced to acknowledge that it is againſt reaſon to diſcredit the revealed will of God, becauſe we ſee not ſufficient reaſon for his will. It was an excellent reſolution of <hi>Socrates,</hi> who when he had learned from <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> (who therefore was ſurnamed <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (that is, <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or <hi>Vnderſtanding</hi>) was the cauſe of all things,<note place="margin">Plato, in <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done.</hi>
                  </note> reſolved he would trouble himſelf no longer to ſeek the naturall cauſe or reaſon of every thing, but reſt in this fully ſatisfied, that ſince <hi>Reaſon</hi> was the ſupream cauſe, all things muſt of neceſſity, both in reſpect of the generall, and of every particular thing, be for the beſt. He was in the right certainly, and till we come to that, our ſcruples will never be at an end.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:113795:34"/>
               <p>Yet one reaſon or conſideration more I find expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the Scripture, which muſt not be omitted; which is, that by this myſtery ſo contrived and brought to paſſe (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>the manifold wiſdome of God</hi> might be made known both to Angels and to men. <hi>Vnto me</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.8, 9, 10, 11.</note> his words are full of weight and holy vigor) <hi>who am leſſe then the leaſt of all Saints is this grace given, that I ſhould preach among the Gentiles the unſearchable riches of Chriſt: And to make all men ſee what is the fellowſhip of the myſtery, which from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world had been hid in God, who created all things in Jeſus Chriſt: To the intent that now unto the Principalities and Powers in heavenly places might bee known by the Church the manifold wiſdome of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This manifold wiſdome of God, though it be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable in all the particulars of this great myſtery from the firſt <hi>Conception</hi> to the <hi>Aſcenſion;</hi> yet it is moſt eminently diſcernible in the circumſtances of his <hi>Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> as the main part of the ſtory. Should a man col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect into one the ſeverall obſervations of ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and other Writers in this kind, it would ariſe to a conſiderable bulk: and though it cannot be denyed that in ſo many, ſome may be found which may ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour more of wit, then weight; yet thoſe ought not to be any prejudice to the ſolidity of the reſt: of which kind there will be enough found to fill the moſt ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, if not extreamly dulled with prophaneneſſe and infidelity, both with delight and with admiration. I have not propoſed to my ſelf ſo large a ſcope, neither am I at this time furniſhed for that purpoſe. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of this kind to the Incarnation more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or at leaſt, to the myſtery in generall, relating, we
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:113795:34"/> have here collected and ſet down.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that as all things were at the firſt created (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>by the Word,</hi> (called in the Greek <hi>Logos</hi>) ſo by the fame <hi>Word,</hi> the reſtauration of mankind alſo, (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the logicall creatures,</hi> as Philoſophers call them) ſhould bee.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that as by the tranſgreſſion of one man, all were made guilty; ſo by the righteouſneſſe of one, all might be acquitted.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that as pride and infidelity were the two principall cauſes of <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, and by it, of the ruine of mankind; ſo faith and humility ſhould bee the means of his reſtauration. Once man in the pride of his heart attempted to be like unto God: and God by a myſtery of humility became like unto man, that he might exalt man to a neerer degree of likeneſſe unto God.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, a woman was the Devils unhappy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument to draw <hi>Adam</hi> to ſin; and of a woman came the Saviour of the world. <hi>Eve</hi> beleeved a wicked Angel (in the form of a Serpent) and tranſgreſſed: <hi>Mary</hi> (that <hi>bleſſed</hi> Virgin) beleeved a bleſſed Angel, and conceived.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, that <hi>after that in the wiſdome of God</hi> (that is,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.21.</note> in the Book of nature; the ſight and contemplation of this Univerſe, which doth ſo manifeſtly ſet forth the infinite power and wiſdome of the Creator) <hi>the world by wiſdome knew not God;</hi> (that he is a Spirit; but one, and onely to be worſhipped) <hi>it pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſſe of preaching</hi> (not grounded upon hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ratiocination, philoſophy, or eloquency of words) <hi>to confound the wiſe,</hi> (ver. 27.) <hi>and to ſave them
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:113795:35"/> that beleeve:</hi> which by the Gentiles was generally much ſcorned and derided, who accounted <hi>beleef,</hi> the character and property of an Idiot.</p>
               <p>We meddle not here with his Nativity, the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances and conſiderations whereof are many, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from thoſe of his Incarnation, and from the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall conſideration of this myſtery. In which kind be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe we have inſiſted upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, many more may be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, that have already by divers been made; and ſome made perchance, that have not yet been obſerved. <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> an ancient learned Writer &amp; Martyr, in his <hi>Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith very well; <hi>The great myſtery of the divine Incarnation ſtill continues a myſtery, not onely for that being proportionably to the ſtrength of them that are ſaved by it, manifeſted, that which is not manifeſted of it is much more then that which is: but alſo becauſe even that which is manifeſted, may be ſaid ſtill hidden</hi> (or, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed) as not, in the truth of it, utterable by any words:</hi> (or, <hi>not comprehenſible to the underſtanding of man.</hi>) So he; and he goes on, and inſiſts in this and the next Chapter, in ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry particulars, which I forbear to tranſlate. Neither his language nor his conceptions are ordinary. They that can read him in his own language, may underſtand him; not they, I doubt, that ſhall reade him tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>It is<note n="a" place="margin">Plato in Phaed. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Plato's</hi> obſervation, that in beleef there may be a kind of unbeleef; when a man by ſatisfactory proofs or evidences being fully convicted in his underſtanding, that the thing is ſo indeed; is nevertheleſſe not only
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:113795:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> by the greatneſſe &amp; ſublimity of the things themſelves that are propoſed; but alſo by the conſideration of the means and vileneſſe of man ſo confounded and amazed, as that at the ſame time he neither knows how to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, nor yet can tell how to contradict. In joy alſo, if exceſſive, there is a kind of unbeleef, whereof we read, <hi>Luke</hi> 24.41. <hi>And whileſt they yet beleeved not for joy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ita &amp; apud Comicum qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam ſuam in re praeſenti &amp; certâ excuſat incredulitatem; <hi>Neſcio, niſi quia tam miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rè hoc eſſe cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pio verum, cò vereor magis.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and wondered.</hi> Whileſt the text ſaith, <hi>they beleeved not for joy,</hi> it ſaith alſo that they beleeved; for elſe, whence was their joy? He who in the conſideration of this myſtery never had any experience of this kind of unbeleef, it may be doubted whether he ever did much fixe his thoughts upon the conſideration of it.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, (as a man may gather from his words) found it no very eaſie buſineſſe, &amp; therefore with ſuch zeal and fervency addreſſed himſelf to God for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; as where he prays for the <hi>Epheſians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 3.16, 17, 18, 19.</note> 
                  <hi>That God would grant them according to the riches of his glory, to bee ſtrengthned with might in the inner man: That Chriſt might dwell in their hearts, that being rooted and grounded in love, They might be able to comprehend with all Saints what is the breadth, and length, and depth, and height: And to know the love of God which paſſeth knowledg, that they might be filled with all the fulneſſe of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By which words and others to the ſame purpoſe, Ch. 1.v.16, 17, 18 19. doth appear that although he thought the mattter, incomprehenſible; yet the frequent me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation and contemplation of it, neceſſary. It is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of ſigular good uſe to wean us from the world: to purge us altogether from the groſſeſt; and to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and allay in us the beſt of earthly affections: and we may certainly conclude, that whoſoever by
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:113795:36"/> a ſettled and conſtant arbitration of his minde or judgement, doth propoſe to himſelf the things of this world (wealth, honour, or life) as much conſiderable, either never ſeriouſly beleeved, or doth not actually beleeve this ſacred myſtery of Chriſt the Son of God his <hi>Incarnation</hi> for the redemption of mankind.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:113795:36"/>
               <head>Of Chriſt his <hi>EXINANITION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing to treat of Chriſt his <hi>Exinanition</hi> by its ſelf as diſtinct from his <hi>Incarnation,</hi> we muſt of neceſſity begin with the word it ſelf, and the different uſes and notions of it in this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred argument.</p>
               <p>This word then <hi>Exinanition</hi> applied to Chriſt, is taken (the word we ſay; for the matter of it is found elſewhere alſo) from the words of the Apoſtle, to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> where, (in the ſecond chap. and third verſe) exhorting them to meekneſſe and humility, <hi>Let nothing be done through ſtrife and vain-glory, &amp;c.</hi> in the ſixth and following verſes he propoſes unto them the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Chriſt in theſe words: <hi>Let this mind be in you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2.5, 6, 7, 8.</note> 
                  <hi>which was alſo in Chriſt Jeſus: Who being in the form of God, thought it not robbery to be equall with God. But made himſelf of no reputation, and took upon him the form of a ſervant, and was made in the likeneſſe of men: And being found in faſhion as a man, he humbled himſelf, and became obedient unto death, even the death of the Croſſe.</hi> Where we render it, <hi>but made himſelf of no reputation;</hi> it is in the Originall, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; tranſlated by the Vulgar, <hi>ſed ſeipſum exinanivit,</hi> and by <hi>Beza, ſed ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſe exinanivit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As, concerning thoſe words in the ſixth verſe, <hi>Who being in the form of God;</hi> with <hi>Arrians</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> who deny the Deity and eternity of Chriſt, there is not little conteſtation about the true meaning; ſo concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:113795:37"/> theſe, <hi>the form of a ſervant,</hi> in the ſeventh, with thoſe (called commonly <hi>Lutherans</hi>) who maintain a reall <hi>communion,</hi> or <hi>communication of proprieties;</hi> whereof we have treated before. There is alſo no ſmall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie concerning the right ſenſe of thoſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which we tranſlate, <hi>thought it not rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Diatriba,</hi> De Verb uſu, &amp;c.</note> of which I have had occaſion to treat elſewhere at large; where, upon good grounds (as I conceive) it is ſhewed, that the words import, <hi>he made it not a matter of triumph,</hi> or <hi>oſtentation:</hi> by which interpretation the Orthodox ſenſe of the former words, <hi>(who being in the form of God)</hi> is much confirmed, and the moſt plauſible objections againſt it, taken away. But this will not concern us here.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Exinanition</hi> then of Chriſt is here in theſe words of the Apoſtle grounded (in the firſt place) in that hee took upon him the <hi>forme of a ſervant:</hi> which words both in oppoſition to the former, <hi>the forme of God;</hi> and as they are further expounded by the Apoſtle himſelf in the words following, <hi>in the likeneſſe of men;</hi> and, <hi>in the faſhion like a man;</hi> muſt needs imply the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eſſence and nature of man, as principally intended; yet with an aggravation, as if he had ſaid, not the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and nature of man onely, but of an abject, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, miſerable man: which is included in the word <hi>ſervant.</hi> Hence it is that the ancient Fathers uſe the words <hi>Exinanitio,</hi> and <hi>forma fervi,</hi> very frequently, in a double ſenſe: underſtanding by it oftentimes, the <hi>Incarnation</hi> of Chriſt; or, his aſſuming of the humane nature, barely: and ſometimes, the low condition; the perſonall reproaches and ſufferings of that humane nature which he aſſumed. Certainly, in Chriſt his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:113795:37"/> Incarnation, was his greateſt abaſement, that the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, the Creator of men and Angels, would ſtoop ſo low, as to be made man; a creature: in which word, though it ſhould not be added, ſo vile a creature as man, or ſo deſpicable a man; the loweſt fall of abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may be thought comprehended. <hi>Homo ſum; hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani à me nihil alienum puto:</hi> there is no kind of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, but may be conceived incidentall and in ſome ſort naturall unto man. But that the Infinite, Eternall, Omnipotent, would be man, that he might ſuffer, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all that can be ſaid, or conceived, or indeed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved by naturall man.</p>
               <p>But on the other ſide, becauſe the ſame Chriſt, as true man by his Incarnation; and as man conſidered, ſubject to ſufferings; ſo he continued nevertheleſſe as truly and entirely what he was before, Infinite, Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, Omnipotent; that he ſhould, though in his hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature onely, ſuffer, can as little be conceived, had not the Deity, ſo far for a time, (though not by any ſeparation) withdrawn or withheld its influence, as to leave the humane nature obnoxious to whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bare humanity (ſin always excepted) was capable of. So that here is Exinanition upon Exinanition: And ſo may Chriſt rightly enough, and agreeably to antiquity (though there is much conteſting between ſome Proteſtants of the Lutheran Confeſſion, and ſome others about it) be ſaid to have been abaſed, or exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanited according to both natures; this always pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſed and underſtood, that the divine nature in Chriſt, did not by this abaſement or Exinanition (which cannot be conceived without blaſphemy) ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any manner of change or alteration.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:113795:38"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exinanition</hi> (as by learned men hath been obſerved) is alſo taken ſometimes by ſome Ancients in a more generall ſenſe, (grounded perchance upon the words of the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.6. <hi>Who humbleth himſelf, &amp;c.</hi>) for that affection of mercy and compaſſion, which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved God to take notice of mans miſery through <hi>Adams</hi> fall, and thereupon to order his redemption and reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration by his Son.</p>
               <p>Of Chriſt his <hi>Exinanition</hi> in the firſt and chiefeſt ſenſe wee have treated hitherto under the notion of his <hi>Incarnation.</hi> Our purpoſe here in the remainder of our <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> is, to conſider his <hi>Exinanition</hi> in the temporall eſtate and condition of his aſſumed fleſh; in thoſe things that Chriſt ſuffered in the courſe of his life before his Paſſion, not ſo much in the perſon or relation of a <hi>Mediator,</hi> or <hi>Redeemer,</hi> (his chiefeſt Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice) as of a <hi>Maſter</hi> or <hi>Teacher,</hi> to be an example of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, humility, perfect obedience and mortification, or contempt of the world, unto us. That Chriſt in all his ſufferings, even the greateſt, his death and paſſion, had a further end (beſides our redemption) to be <hi>an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample unto us,</hi> is directly affirmed by Saint <hi>Peter:</hi> and that the ſame Chriſt in his more ordinary ſufferings, (though we acknowledge his merits, or meriting to us too in all that he did or ſuffered) as his poverty, and the like, his chief end and aim was to be an example unto us, if it be not directly affirmed by the Scriptures, may with much probability grounded upon the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, be ſuppoſed and inferred. Why Chriſt, for example, though he might (as ſome Ancients obſerve) after a more apparently miraculous way have been made true man, muſt be born of a woman, many good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:113795:38"/> may be given: but why he ſhould chuſe an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Village, or a common Inne, or a Manger in the Inne, to be places (in ſeverall reſpects) of his Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, the moſt probable reaſon can be given, is, that he might be an example of humility unto us.</p>
               <p>In this ſenſe then it is, and with this particular relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that I ſhal now ſpeak of Chriſt his <hi>Exinanition;</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the firſt thing will be, to conſider how it is propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to us in the Scripture. I will not amplifie matters, but content my ſelf with the bare relation of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel. It is a ſubject, I confeſſe, fit for the beſt rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of the world; wherein ancient Fathers and Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have not been deficient. I like well of ſuch ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications, as tend to make a deeper impreſſion in us, (ſuch is our dulneſſe) of what we can never be too ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. But ſome men have not contained themſelves within thoſe bounds. As though they would rather ſupply the defect of the Scriptures, then of our devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, they tell us of many things, deviſed by themſelves which the Scriptures doe not; and of a ſacred hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, by this mixture, make (as far as in them lies) a kind of <hi>Legend. Papias</hi> of old was taxed for this; and many ſince him, have been guilty of the ſame fault. But to leave them:</p>
               <p>The Scriptures tel us that the bleſſed Mother of Chriſt, about the very time that he was to be born, was forced to travell: that ſhe was delivered in a common Inne, and the born child Chriſt Jeſus, for want of other room in the Inne, (taken up in all likelihood by greater gueſts) was laid in a Manger. That aſſoon as he was born, he was perſecuted; and thereupon his true mother and reputed father (with him, their charge and care) put to
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:113795:39"/> the troubles and toils of a long Journey into a ſtrange Country, for refuge. That Chriſt did ever work with his own hands, is not ſo clearly expreſſed in the ſacred ſtory; but that he was ſubject to his parents, (his repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted father being a Carpenter by his trade) is clearly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed: and becauſe Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Mark</hi> 6.3. by ſome, to whom his life and converſation was well known, is called a <hi>Carpenter, Juſtin Martyr</hi> his opinion is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by many; who peremptorily doth determine it, that Chriſt himſelf did work. And beſides, though no other Scripture ſhould induce us to beleeve it, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we are taught that Chriſt was <hi>made a curſe for us, Gal.</hi> 3.13. and that he was <hi>ſent in the likeneſſe of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fleſh,</hi> Rom. 8.3. it ſtands with great probability, to ſay no more, that he ſhould in the courſe of his life find and feel the effect of that curſe, by God himſelf ſo ſolemnly pronounced, <hi>In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eat bread, Gen.</hi> 3.9.</p>
               <p>Again, that after he had openly and ſolemnly ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon his Miniſtery, he ſubſiſted, in part at leaſt, by almes and contributions, is particularly recorded. That he went up and downe, doing good, yet almoſt every where ſuffering evill: evill words, evill reports, affronts, reproaches: frequent attempts, upon his life and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency: perſecuted in his own perſon; and perſecuted in them that adhered unto him, or ſpake well of him; we find in the ſame Scriptures. Briefly, his own words of himſelf, <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.20. <hi>The Foxes have holes, and the Birds of the aire have neſts: but the Son of man hath not where to lay his head:</hi> are above all amplifications, and all rhetorick that the wit or eloquence of man can reach unto. If this be not enough to ſet out this <hi>Exinanition</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:113795:39"/> of Chriſt, we might have recourſe to the Prophet <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay,</hi> who alſo is very pregnant and patheticall in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of it: <hi>Eſa.</hi> the 52. and 53. Chap. but it ſhall ſuffice to have named him: the Reader himſelf, if hee pleaſe, may have recourſe unto him.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe not the Jews onely, who miſtaking the Prophets, expected an earthly King for their <hi>Meſsias;</hi> but divers others alſo in all ages, worldly-minded men, or weak men, have been much ſcandalized at this manner of the Son of God his appearing <hi>in the form of a ſervant:</hi> before we ſpeak of it in relation to us, (the main end of it) we will conſider of it by it ſelf, a while, what from beſt humane reaſon may be ſaid for ſuch a condition of life. For if it ſhall appear, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that the contempt of all worldly pomp and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, upon grounds of reaſon in the judgement of the moſt rationall and judicious Heathens, Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers and others, hath been accounted a more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous thing, then the proſecution of it; but alſo more bleſſedneſſe, with patience and calmneſſe of mind to undergoe all manner of croſſes and adverſities in this life, then to enjoy pleaſure and to live at eaſe; I hope all exceptions and prejudices in this kind, which humane wit can with any colour ſuggeſt to the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of our faith concerning the Author of our ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will ſufficiently be removed.</p>
               <p>To the firſt then: The moſt ordinary both, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious definition or character of one that is truly magnanimous or generous, occurrent in the writings of ancient Heathens, is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to whom nothing (in this life, nor life it ſelf) ſeems a great matter:</hi> that is, greatly conſiderable. But more particularly, this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:113795:40"/> or <hi>nothing,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ariſt. <hi>De virtut.</hi>
                  </note> is thus expreſſed by <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in a place: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſaith he, &amp;c. <hi>It is alſo the part and property of true magnanimity, not to admire neither pleaſure, nor greatneſs, nor power, nor victories obtained at the ſolemn games and prizes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They that are not acquainted with the ſtate of the world as it was in thoſe days (when certainly it was, in many reſpects, at a farre greater height of glory and outward ſplendor, then now it is) will not underſtand the pertinency (though moſt proper of it ſelf) of that inſtance, <hi>of victories obtained at ſolemn games and prizes.</hi> His intention was certainly to goe to the higheſt of humane glory, that his expreſſion could reach, or his phanſie pitch upon: and ſuch was the glory of thoſe <hi>ſolemn victories</hi> he ſpeaks of. For firſt, (to help them a little that are not acquainted with Antiquity) what was done there, was not done in the ſight of one Nation or Kingdome onely, but in the ſight, and concourſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>of the whole earth,</hi> as ancient Authours te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie. And ſuch was the honour of the Conquerors, and ſuch their priviledges; that they were, not after their lives onely, ſome of them, worſhipped as Gods; but even in their life time accounted moſt of them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every where, (to uſe their own word) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>as gods;</hi> or <hi>equall unto the gods.</hi> And it is further obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the moſt famous <hi>Epocha,</hi> or computation of times that ever was among Heathens (the <hi>Olympiades</hi>) was taken from theſe ſports and victories, as if they had been the thing, wherein the world was moſt intereſſed, or which to take notice of, it moſt concerned it.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> ſo others, al, or moſt that I have ſeen, make this the proper character of true magnanimity, <hi>not to
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:113795:40"/> admire;</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Dionyſ. Longinus in praeſtantiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> libello, elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſime, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Et paulò poſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> (as by others it is expreſſed) <hi>to deſpiſe</hi> all thoſe things which by ordinary men are highly prized and eſteemed. Now the conſiderations upon which they grounded this contempt of the world, were theſe eſpecially:</p>
               <p>Firſt, the ſhort continuance, if not of the objects them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of glory, which this world preſented unto us; yet of that fruition of them this our mortall life doth afford; being compared to eternity. <hi>Quae verò aetas lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga eſt?</hi> ſaith one of them. <hi>What age of man is long? Or what is it indeed, that to mortall man can truly be deemed and tearmed long? But a very little while agoe we were boyes; then young men; and behold how old age, whileſt we were in our race, ſuddenly, even before we could think or ſuſpect, hath overtaken us. And this we call long, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe old age to us is our utmoſt bounds. For ſo it is, that according to the meaſure of continuance allotted by nature unto every thing, ſo is age generally accounted either ſhort or long.</hi> Ariſtotle <hi>writes of certain little creatures about the River Hypanis, (which from ſome part of Europe doth flow into the Pontus) which live but one day; Of theſe little creatures therefore ſuch as live till about the third or fourth houre after noon paſt, dies in good age: but thoſe that live to the going down of the Sun, decrepit; eſpecially if it be a Summers day, when the dayes are at longeſt. Let us compare our longeſt age with eternity, and we ſhall finde their lives and ours to come much to one reckoning. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe we therefore ſuch fopperies (for what elſe to call, or how more gently to tearm things that are ſo light and vain, I know not) and let us account true courage and magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, deſpiſing all humane things, and wholly ſet upon the purſuit of vertue, the ſole happineſſe of man.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:113795:41"/>
               <p>So another; and he might ſpeak with more autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as being then in actuall poſſeſſion of as much great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſplendor as the whole earth could well afford, (or ever did afford) unto one man: a puiſſant Prince and Monarch:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marcus Aur. Antoninus,</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perator, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, lib. 5. C § 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Often meditate,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>how ſwiftly all things that ſubſiſt, and all things that are done in the world, are carried away, and as it were conveyed out of ſight. For both the ſubſtances themſelves (we ſee) as a flood, are in a continuall fluxe: and all actions, in a perpetuall change: and the cauſes themſelves ſubject to a thouſand alterations: neither is there any thing almoſt, that may be ſaid to be now ſetled, and conſtant</hi> (or <hi>at a ſtand.) Next unto this, and which follows upon it, conſider both the infiniteneſſe of the time already paſſed</hi> (this is ſpoken by him as a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, who did not know the beginning of the world, nor beleeve perchance that it ever had a beginning) <hi>and the immenſe vaſtneſſe of that which is to come, wherein all things are to be reſolved and annihilated. Art not thou then a very fool, who for theſe things art either puffed up with pride, or diſtracted with cares; or, as for a thing that would trouble thee for any ſpace of time, (to ſpeak of) canſt find in thy heart to make ſuch moanes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another main conſideration that induced them to this contempt, is the ſmalneſſe, or pettineſſe (if I may ſo ſpeak) of the earth (the principall object of mortall men's cares and affections) in reſpect of the whole world or Univerſe. A conſideration, not grounded (as ſome might happily ſurmiſe) upon the meer ſubtilty of Aſtronomicall ſpeculations; or extravagant bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of rhetoricall amplifications; but upon ſuch evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences of common ſenſe and reaſon, as any rationall man (with very little ſearch and ſtudy) is capable of.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:113795:41"/> Yea and to this very end God and Nature (in the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of ancient Heathens) have made man capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſuch knowledge and contemplation, that he might not ſet his minde upon the earth or earthly things, it being very improbable, if not impoſſible, that he that hath a right apprehenſion of this Univerſe, and uſeth himſelf (as becomes him) now and then to ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate his thoughts to ſuch contemplations, ſhould be much taken or affected with things ſo vile and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, as all ſublunary things will be found, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to the Univerſe; and ſo much inferiour to the divine temper and conſtitution of mans ſoul and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. <hi>Quid enim videatur ei magnum in rebus humanis, cui aeternitas omnis, totiuſque mundi nota ſit mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitudo?</hi> So <hi>Tully;</hi> and the ſame in another place, <hi>Idem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que cum coelum, terras, maria, omniumque rerum naturam perſpexerit,—in hac ille magnificentiâ rerum, atque in hoc conſpectu &amp; cognitione naturae, Dii immortales, quàm ipſe ſe noſcet, (quod Apollo praecepit Pythius) quàm con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnet, quàm deſpiciet, quàm pro nihilo putabit ea, quae vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gò dicuntur ampliſsima?</hi> that is, <hi>The ſame man when hee ſhall underſtand the nature of the Heavens, of the Earth, the Sea, and all that belongs unto them—in this magnificence of things, in this ſight and ſurvay of nature, good God! how will he (as the Oracle commandeth) begin to know him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; how will he contemn, and deſpiſe, and account as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thoſe things, which among men ordinarily, are in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt account and eſteem?</hi> and the writings of ancient Grecians, that write of Philoſophy, are full of ſuch paſſages.</p>
               <p>It is ſo certainly: And if there be not among men now adays (as certainly there are not) ſuch examples
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:113795:42"/> of heroick ſpirits and of true magnanimity, as have been in former times, among the Grecians eſpecially; it may very probably be conceived, that one maine reaſon of it is, becauſe the <hi>Mathematicks</hi> (Aſtronomy and Aſtrology were ſo called anciently) are not ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally ſtudied, as they were formerly, among the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians eſpecially. For it is one thing to hear in ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry talk (as it is commonly talked) that the Earth to the whole Univerſe is but as one point, which many may conceive to be but an hyperbolicall ſpeech, as if wee called a little man, an atome, in compariſon of a great mountain: another thing, upon certain grounds of ſenſe and reaſon,<note place="margin">Ptol. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> l. <hi>1.</hi> § <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as by <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> and other Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians it is demonſtrated, to know it and apprehend it clearly; as clearly, as every ordinary capacity doth apprehend, that one ſingle fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thing, is no very conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable thing, (little more then nothing) in compariſon of ſuch a ſum; as for example, of one hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Engliſh pounds.</p>
               <p>Theſe things therefore whoever ſhall rightly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and underſtand, as he looketh upon a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth of Ants or Bees,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp;. <hi>Anton.</hi> De Scipſo, <hi>l</hi> 7. § 3. Formi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iſte diſcurſus eſt in anguſto labe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantium. Quid illis &amp; nobis intereſt, &amp;c. <hi>Sen. Nat. Qu. l.</hi> 1. <hi>in Praef.</hi>
                  </note> (it is the ſimilitude uſed by divers upon this occaſion) where he ſeeth great ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and pains taking; much carrying and running to and fro: ſo will he look upon the ordinary cares and diſtractions, frights and fears, hopes and joys of ſuch among the ſons of men, whoſe mindes are whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet upon the world, and have no further aim.</p>
               <p>A third conſideration that induced them to this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, is, becauſe this world (in the ordinary courſe of the world) affordeth nothing ſo great and glorious, but the baſeſt and vileſt of men are as capable of, as the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:113795:42"/> moſt generous and deſerving. Wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> obſerved it, and he made a good uſe of it, it made him thinke the leſſe of his own greatneſſe.<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.11.</note> 
                  <hi>I returned</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and ſaw under the Sun, that the race is not to the ſwift, nor the battell to the ſtrong; neither yet bread to the wiſe, nor yet riches to men of underſtanding, nor yet favour to men of skill; but time and chance hapneth to them all,</hi> Eccleſ. 9.11. <hi>Theſe worldly goods,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>how baſe,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (ſaith the <hi>Solomon</hi> of the Heathens; <hi>Quae turpiſſimo cuique ac contemptiſsimo, leno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ac laniſtae, poſſunt contingere;</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca) which may be in the power and poſſeſſion of ſome abominable looſe liver, ſome common ſtrumpet, or ſome ravenous and bloudy Tyrant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It once troubled <hi>Pliny</hi> the later, (a man of great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and great place in the Roman Common-wealth) very much, (when he obſerved what honourable titles the Senate of Rome (whereof himſelf had the honor to be a member) had conferred upon ſuch a ſlave, (<hi>furciferum,</hi> as he cals him) as <hi>Pallas</hi> was: what honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Edicts</hi> and <hi>Declarations</hi> they had made in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half; ſuch indeed (they are to be ſeen in <hi>Pliny</hi>) as ſcarce any, the moſt renowned for valour, or wiſdome, or noble deſcent, whom former times had known, had ever obtained. It did put him upon this contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (the beſt uſe indeed that can be made of ſuch ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects) <hi>quàm mimica &amp; inepta eſſent, quae interdum in hoc coenum, in has ſordes abjicerentur, how vile and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptible ſuch things muſt needs be, which were caſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times upon ſuch dunghils. Tacitus</hi> writes of this <hi>Pallas,</hi> that he had an eſtate of <hi>ter millies:</hi> which doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to ſuch a vaſt ſum of money, as might now ſuffice to be a ranſome for many great Kings.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:113795:43"/>
               <p>By this appears what account wiſe Heathens made of the greatneſſe of this world: and if this contempt of the world became them well, and was eſteemed in them an effect of trueſt magnanimity, whoſe hopes never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe (for the moſt of them) went not beyond this world: how much more (upon their own grounds) muſt it become him, who both as he was the Eternall Son of God, from all eternity had in himſelf all fulneſſe of infinite content and bleſſedneſſe and in the beginning of times, had created Heaven and Earth, the Heaven <hi>to be his throne,</hi> and the <hi>Earth his foot-ſtool: (Eſay</hi> 66.1.) and as he was <hi>made fleſh</hi> in the fulneſſe of times, yet even then was ſo united to eternall Majeſty, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven then he was <hi>the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f glory;</hi> and ſo much the more <hi>the Lord of glory,</hi> becauſe he had it in himſelf and from himſelf wholly, not from any outward adventitious lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre. That infinite diſproportion betweene the leaſt glimpſe of Eternall Majeſty, and the greateſt glory this earth doth afford, how could it better appear upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, then in contempt of the earth? He that had the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in himſelf, ſhould he ſeek after the ſhadow? <hi>Cui nihil ad augendum faſtigium ſupereſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plia. Sec. in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negyr.</hi> ad Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>janum.</note> 
                  <hi>hic uno mode creſcere poteſt, ſi ſe ipſe ſubmittat, ſecurus magnitudinis ſuae. Hee that is at the height of Majeſty and Greatneſſe, if he will yet be greater and higher, he muſt abaſe himſelfe, ſhewing his Greatneſſe in that more then in any thing, that he can abaſe himſelf with ſecurity.</hi> This was counſel once given to a great Prince and Emperour, by a great Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor: Heathens, both: and this we may ſay was the caſe of Chriſt: It was moſt proper to him, above all men, to magnifie himſelf in his humility, who was ſo farre above all men; as being both God and man.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:113795:43"/>
               <p>Were there no other argument to perſwade men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the opinion of the <hi>Millenaries,</hi> this would much move me: An earthly Kingdome of a thouſand years? They muſt think better of the Earth, then I doe; and a thouſand years, a longer time, then I can conceive it, who propoſe ſuch a Kingdome as a great thing to him, who is Lord of Heaven and Earth; to whom <hi>a thouſand years are as yeſterday, when it is paſt; and as a watch of the night,</hi> Pſal. 90.4.</p>
               <p>There is not any thing that more enhaunceth the credit of men in the world, then the reputation of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and the fame of Conqueſts and Victories. The Scriptures themſelves ſeem to goe this way too: <hi>Gird thy ſword upon thy thigh, O moſt mighty, &amp;c Thine arrows are ſharp, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 45.3.5 &amp;c. which ſpeeches, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers others of the ſame kind, were intended of Chriſt. And the Jews grounding partly upon ſuch places of Scrip ure, and partly upon their own fond thoughts &amp; imaginations, did promiſe themſelves ſuch a <hi>Meſsias</hi> that ſhould not onely be a King, but a Warriour alſo &amp; a great Conqueror. Of this, becauſe approved hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of al ages &amp; nations are ſufficient to inform us what to think of it; and becauſe it is a caſe that concerns the Jews particularly; I ſhall ſay no more then what I find in a learned Jew, of later times, but of great eſteem, <hi>Manaſſe ben ſrael;</hi> in his treatiſe <hi>De Reſurrectione,</hi> where preferring the reſurrection of the dead (in point of glory) to the comming of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> he hath theſe words: <hi>Although it be certain that at the comming of the</hi> Meſſias, <hi>the glorious Name of God ſhall be exalted; yet as certain it is, that it will not be with ſuch glory and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, as it will bee at the reſurrection of the dead.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:113795:44"/> For neither is it indeed ſo great a miracle, if the Meſsias ſhall ſubdue many Kingdomes and Nations; when as it is well known that ſome of very mean quality, and from ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure beginnings have attained to Kingdomes and Empires, and have been Lords of divers Countries. Whereas at the Reſurrection, &amp;c.</hi> So much of Chriſt his humility, in relation to the opinions of ancient Heathens, and what may be ſaid of it in point of humane reaſon.</p>
               <p>As for Chriſt's ſufferings, our next particular, were we to ſpeak of his death and crucifixion particularly, we could not but take notice of a notable paſſage of <hi>Plato's</hi> (a prediction we might call it) much inſiſted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and deſervedly, by ſome Ancients, as <hi>Theodoret, Euſebius,</hi> and ſome others. The paſſage, is that in the ſecond of his <hi>Common-weal,</hi> where propoſing the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of a perfect juſt man, among other things that ſuch a one muſt undergoe, that his righteouſneſſe may be approved to God and men to the utmoſt, he doth mention <hi>Crucifixion.</hi> But having to doe here with ſufferings in generall onely, it ſhall be ſufficient in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to ſay, that as to deſpiſe pleaſures and worldly greatneſſe; (whereof we have ſpoken) ſo patiently to endure, and if occaſion be, willingly and readily to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe what ordinary men moſt dread and flie, hath always, among the wiſeſt of men, been deemed an argument of trueſt generoſity and nobleneſſe of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: and not onely ſo, but by many alſo, an argument of Gods love and favour.</p>
               <p>As for the firſt part of my aſſertion, that patiently to endure, and readily to undergoe all manner of croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and calamities, belongs to true magnanimity; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no man that hath read any thing in ancient
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:113795:44"/> Authors, will make any queſtion of it, I ſhall not need any proofs to make it good. But that croſſes and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities ſhould be an argument of Gods love and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, may not without ſome reaſon ſeeme either a meer paradox of the Stoick, or a ſecret of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an philoſophy. There be indeed in the writings of thoſe Philoſophers, that were called Stoicks, divers expreſſions to be found to this purpoſe, that goe beyond all that I have read in the moſt rigid and reſolute Chriſtian Authors. Might I take the advantage of ſuch, I ſhould not need to ſeek any further at all. But becauſe the Philoſophers of that ſect, were charged by many to hold things contrary to nature and common ſenſe, though themſelves did extreamly diſclaim it, and as confidently boaſted of the contrary, that their doctrine was altogether founded upon nature; and which is more, drew after them a great part of the world; yet I will not altogether rely upon them, but farther add, which I conceive to be very obſervable, that ſome whom from all Antiquity the Heathens generally honoured as greateſt Favourites of their moſt honoured Deities, were ſet out unto them as greateſt ſufferers in the whole courſe of their lives. Such were, <hi>Hercules,</hi> the ſon (as they feigned) of <hi>Juppiter:</hi> of whoſe labours, who hath not heard? and <hi>Vlyſſes;</hi> of whom <hi>Maximus Tyrius</hi> (conformably to what others have written of him more at large) recordeth, that God forced him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>to wander and to beg, and to wear rags; to be kicked and reviled;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>for the love that he did bear unto him:</hi> which puts me in minde of <hi>Epictetus</hi> his famous Diſtick concerning himſelf:
<q>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:113795:45"/>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>.</note>Epictetus, a ſlave; in my body maimed:</l>
                     <l>No man ever poorer: of the Gods beloved.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Epictetus,</hi> (a poore man indeed, whileſt he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) when he dyed, of all worldly goods left after him but one poor Lamp; but ſuch a name and ſuch a repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation with it, as made his memory ſacred to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt of the earth; ſo that this very Lamp for his ſake became very precious, and proved a competent patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to them that ſold it.</p>
               <p>Hitherto we have ſpoken of Chriſt his <hi>Exinanition,</hi> in relation to Chriſt himſelf, as he was the Son of God; what in point of humane reaſon might be ſaid of it, or for it, againſt the ſcoffs and exceptions of men preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to reaſon and common ſenſe; as alſo, for the further ſatisfaction of ſome weaker Chriſtians. We are now to treat of it in relation to us; and firſt, as it might tend to our inſtruction, or confirmation of faith.</p>
               <p>There is not any point of doctrine more neceſſary to be known, beleeved and preſſed among men, then the doctrine of the immortality of the ſoul, and of a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment after this life. It is the main fundamentall of all piety and godlineſſe. <hi>If the dead riſe not, Let us eate and drink, for to morrow we die:</hi> was Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence; though perchance not ſo much his own ſenſe and inference properly, as the ſenſe and inference of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of men, transferred upon himſelf. <hi>Nonne melius multò fuiſſet;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cicero</hi> De Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nect.</note> 
                  <hi>How much better were it for us to paſſe our lives in eaſe and quietneſſe, without either labour or ſtrife; if ſo be that the ſoul be not immortall indeed?</hi> It was the ſpeech of one, but the ſenſe of moſt ancient Heathens, as partly from their lives, and partly from other ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and expreſſions tending to the ſame purpoſe,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:113795:45"/> might be collected. Now one main argument uſed by ancient Heathens to perſwade themſelves and others that it was ſo indeed; that the ſoul was immortall, and that there was a judgement, or ſomewhat anſwerable to a judgement, after this life, was, as the proſperity of wicked men, ſo the troubles and miſeries of the vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and godly, in all ages of the world, (even among the Jews, when the condition of temporall rewards was more abſolute, then ſince the light of the Goſpel it hath been) by all ſorts of men noted and obſerved. For, ſaid they, the Sun, the Moone, the ſeaſons of the year, and other works of God, ſufficiently teach us, that there is a God, who hath created and appointed theſe things: and as it would be againſt common ſenſe to doubt of the being of a God, ſo is it as much againſt ſenſe, that is, thoſe common notions of humane rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whereby men are naturally guided to diſcern be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween that which is morally good and evill, juſt and unjuſt, to doubt whether God himſelf from whom we have received theſe notions, be good and juſt. Now then ſince we ſee plainly, that in this world there be many juſt men,<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8.14.</note> 
                  <hi>unto whom</hi> (to uſe the words of <hi>Solomon</hi> in ſtead of theirs) <hi>it happeneth according to the work of the wicked;</hi> and again, many <hi>wicked men, unto whom it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth according to the work of the righteous;</hi> it muſt needs be, that after this there is another world, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both good and evill ſhall be rewarded according to their works.</p>
               <p>This argument though uſed by Heathens of old, who were guided by the light of nature onely, yet ought it not therefore to be in leſſe eſteem with Chriſtians.<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mel.</hi> de Animâ <hi>cap. ult.</hi> de im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>immortalit. Haec conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio in bonis men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, &amp;c. <hi>Vide &amp; viru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parab. Hug. Grot. in Matth. 22.32.</hi> Inter omnia argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, quae ad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandam a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imi immortalita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip Melanchthon,</hi> as brave a man both for piety and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as ever <hi>Germany</hi> had, acknowledgeth of himſelf,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:113795:46"/> that he found very good uſe of it, and that his faith was not a little ſtrengthned by it. It may very well be that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf aimed at the ſame thing, where he ſaith, that the ſufferings of the righteous in this world are <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; that is, <hi>a clear evidence</hi> or <hi>demonſtration of Gods judgement:</hi> future, that is; or, that ſhall be. The words will bear this ſenſe and interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion very well: and there be, (as may appear by the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian Notes</hi> upon the place) who ſo interpret thoſe words of Chriſt in Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>And it ſhall turn to you for a teſtimony, Luke</hi> 21.13.</p>
               <p>Now if the conſideration of godly mens ſufferings in this world be of moment to ſuch an inference; how much more the ſufferings of Chriſt, (conſider him but as a man) ſo good and ſo innocent, beyond all exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: &amp; not his ſufferings only, but alſo his contempt of the <hi>good things</hi> of this world, (as they are called, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.2.) who did ſo much good, inſtructing the ſouls, and curing the bodies of ſo many men, whileſt he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the world?</p>
               <p>Of the ancient <hi>Druides,</hi> as I remember, it is record<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſomewhere, that <hi>humana deſpectantes, animam im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalem eſſe pronunciarunt;</hi> that is, <hi>deſpiſing the things of this world they did pronounce,</hi> or <hi>declare the ſoul of man to be immortall.</hi> And whereas of Pope <hi>John</hi> the 22. of that name it is affirmed by ſome, that he denyed the reſurrection of the dead, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith no; but that by reaſon of his lewd life, men did generally conceive that he did not beleeve another life after this, though he did not poſitively maintain any ſuch thing. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Bellarmine</hi> be in the right,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bell.</hi> De Rom. Pontif. <hi>l. 4. c. 14.</hi> § Itaque.</note> or no, concerning this particular inſtance; I ſhall not here enquire; nor yet
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:113795:46"/> enquire more generally, what dependence theſe two, opinions, and actions, have the one upon the other; and whether a man may certainly and infallibly from the one, judge of the other: certain it is that men ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily judge of the opinions of men by what they ſee in their lives and converſations. Chriſt therefore, (to conclude this point) as he taught men by his doctrine, ſo by his <hi>Exinanition,</hi> (the humility of his life, and the multiplicity of his ſufferings) that the ſoul of man is immortall, and that after this life there is a judgement to be expected.</p>
               <p>But laſtly, Chriſt did of purpoſe undergoe this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of humiliation and Exinanition, that he might by his example not only teach us, as before we have ſaid, what to think of this preſent world, but alſo the more powerfully draw us to the contempt of it: being a leſſon of ſuch conſequence to us, as the ſaving of our ſouls, and eternity of either happineſſe, or miſery: God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo provided and appointed it, that Heavens ſhould be opened unto ſuch onely, who by abſtinence, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification, and the like, ſhould make their way. Not that by theſe we can merit Heaven, (which were to void the ſatisfaction of Chriſt, the main foundation of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity) but becauſe theſe are the neceſſary conſequents of a true faith, without which we cannot apply to our ſelves the merits of Chriſt's ſatisfaction. <hi>Love not the world, neither the things that are in the world.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.15, 16, 17.</note> 
                  <hi>If any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him. For all that is in the world, the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life, is not of the Father, but is of the world. And the world paſſeth away, and the luſt thereof: but he that doth the will of God, abideth for ever.</hi> A heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:113795:47"/> doctrine indeed; but the more heavenly, the more hard of digeſtion to naturall man.</p>
               <p>It cannot be denyed, but Chriſt (take him but as a man) uſed ſo much ſolid reaſon, ſo many excellent argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſome drawn from the nature of God, others from the generality of his providence, and the like; and that theſe reaſons, theſe arguments (if of divine Oracles we may be allowed ſo to ſpeak) were ſet out with that rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick, or vigour of expreſſion, (which the Grecians properly call <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) as could not but affect much any ſober rationall man, as would take them into ſerious conſideration. Yet ſo it is, (as by many upon ſeverall occaſions hath been well obſerved) the example of the Orator, is above all reaſons and arguments. <hi>Seneca</hi> hath ſaid as much for poverty and contempt of the world, as ever I think, was ſaid by man, that was meer man, But whileſt he ſpake againſt riches, what by favours from his Prince and pupill; and what by his private nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiations, he heaped them (himſelf doth acknowledge it) beyond all meaſure. His life was not very vicious; but it was very vain and ſumptuous: witneſſe thoſe famous tables, ſo highly valued, that he left after him among other houſhold ſtuffe. No wonder therefore if he did ſo little good while he lived. <hi>Epictetus,</hi> with leſſe wit and rhetorick, did much more. As he wrote, ſo he lived.</p>
               <p>Some men have been of opinion that this <hi>Epictetus</hi> was a Chriſtian. There be indeed in thoſe Remains of his doctrine and ſpeeches preſerved to poſterity by <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianus,</hi> and others, ſome paſſages for the ſubſtance of the matter, ſo Euangelicall, that a man might ſuſpect them to have been borrowed from the writings of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: ſome again ſo particularly appliable to Chriſt, as
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:113795:47"/> might not improbably, by thoſe that look no further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the matter, be ſurmiſed to have been intended of him. But certain it is, that he was not a Chriſtian; all that can be gathered from ſuch paſſages, is, that Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is not ſo much repugnant to humane ſenſe and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, (by good literature well refined and improved) as it hath been by many conceived. In this very particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar we are now upon, treating of the office, parts and duties of one that would take upon himſelf to be a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like teacher; or, as himſelf ſtyles him, <hi>Gods Meſſenger,</hi> to reclaim mankind fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their vain courſes, he preſſeth very much the neceſſity of his example in the contempt of all worldly things, as of pains, ſo of pleaſures, honour, and the like. Among other things to this purpoſe, he hath theſe words: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. <hi>For it behoveth the true Cynick</hi> (the ſame whom in that very Chapter he alſo calleth, <hi>the Meſſenger, the Watchman; the Preacher,</hi> or <hi>Herald; the Miniſter;</hi> yea and <hi>the Apoſtle of God) to have ſuch meaſure of patience,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epictet. Arria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> l. 3. c. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>as to be accounted by moſt men a very ſtock or ſtone. Himſelf indeed</hi> (that is, his ſoul) <hi>to be above the ſtroak, or contumely of men: but as for his body to yeeld that readily to whomſoever, to be uſed at his pleaſure.</hi> And again in another Chapter of the ſame Book, <hi>For theſe things God ſends me hither and thither. He makes me a ſpectacle unto men of poverty, of contempt; of crazineſſe of body; here baniſhed; there a priſoner: not out of any ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to me; (God forbid) how ſhould he hate the beſt of his ſervants? nor out of neglect, (for even the leaſt things are cared for by him) but to exerciſe me, and to uſe me as his witneſſe unto others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fit then and expedient (in point of humane reaſon, at leaſt) it was, that he that came to teach us the way
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:113795:48"/> to Heaven by contempt of the world, ſhould himſelfe lead us the way by his example. This end of Chriſt his <hi>Exinanition,</hi> and this his example is preſſed in divers places of Scripture. <hi>Let this minde be in you,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Philippians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 2.5, 6, &amp;c.</note> as we ſaw before) <hi>which was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in Chriſt Jeſus; Who being in the form of God, &amp;c.</hi> And Saint <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21.</note> to the ſame purpoſe, <hi>For even hereunto were ye called: becauſe Chriſt alſo ſuffered for us, leaving us an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that ye ſhould follow his ſteps.</hi> To this head alſo may be referred ſuch places, where Chriſt is ſet out unto us, as if for his own ſake and intereſt he had undergone what he did, and ſubmitted himſelf to this kind of <hi>Exinaniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> So <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. <hi>Looking upon Jeſus the Author and fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſher of our faith, who for the joy that was ſet before him, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the croſſe, deſpiſing the ſhame, and is ſet down at the right hand of the throne of God.</hi> And in the ſame Epiſtle, Ch. 5.7, 8. <hi>Who in the days of his fleſh, &amp;c. Though he were a Son, yet learned he obedience by the things which he ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: And being made perfect, he became the Author of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſalvation unto all them that obey him. Though he were a Son,</hi> that is, as I take it, that although Chriſt was in an extraordinary manner the Son of God, born without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtain of originall ſin, &amp;c. yet having undertaken ſuch a charge and ſuch an office as he had, it was conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent he ſhould under goe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, troubles and adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in this life, not onely that by divers degrees of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings in the courſe of his life he might the better be prepared (as ſome here doe paraphraſe) for his great and laſt ſuffering, the principal end of his Incarnation; nor as bearing that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>likeneſs of ſinfull fleſh, (Rom.</hi> 8.3.) but alſo by his example the more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to teach and ſatisfie us, that even they that are dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:113795:48"/> unto God among the ſons of men, muſt by trials and croſſes in this world, be fitted for God &amp; another world.</p>
               <p>And indeed as the example (apprehended with a right and lively faith) was incomparable, ſo did there enſue ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects anſwerable; that is, admirable beyond all example. Of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great (not to inſtance in others) by Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians that have written his life, or of him, it is noted that by his example eſpecially, he did atchieve moſt of his greateſt exploits in the Conqueſt of the world. When ever he was much put to it, as either hardly beſet (himſelf and his Army, as he was often) with inextricable difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; or would put his ſoldiers upon ſome deſperate action, beyond the compaſſe of ordinary humane ſtrength and courage; his example was his ordinary refuge, &amp; conſtant ſtratagem, which ſeldome or never failed him. Among o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things which he did in this kind, this ſeems to me as memorable as any. His Army which was wont to be light &amp; expedit, laden with the ſpoils of many rich Countries, marched but heavily. Neither could their heads be free, when their hands were ſo full. Being thus, what vvith care, what with loadage much encumbred, <hi>Alexander</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending the conſequence of this alteration, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing well enough that with words (for ſooner would they have parted with their lives, then with that for which they had all hazarded; and many of them loſt their lives, ſay the Hiſtorians) he ſhould doe but little good, he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded all his own Carriages, not ſparing any; and all theirs, to be brought into one place. Then he command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fire to be ſet, not to theirs, but to his: but the fire ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſoon conſumed all that was there, as well of theirs, as his own. And how could they mourn or murmure for their mites, (in compariſon) that ſaw their King ſo free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to devote his own rich treaſures?</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:113795:49"/>
               <p>It were ſtrange that <hi>Alexander</hi> his example ſhould have more influence upon his ſouldiers, then the example of Chriſt upon thoſe that are called by his name; the diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion both of the perſons, and of the obligations on both ſides being conſidered. Chriſt indeed was not him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf always preſent in perſon; and when preſent <hi>in the days of his fleſh,</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh) yet not viſible to bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily eyes, in his Majeſty, as <hi>Alexander</hi> was. But where the eyes of faith have been opened, effects of Chriſt's example have enſued, beyond all compariſon. In the time of the Primitive Church, when the memory of Chriſt his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation upon earth, and of his miracles, was yet freſh, Chriſtians were generally known by nothing more then for their contempt of the world, and of death particularly. It was objected unto them by Heathens who were not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the myſteries of their faith, as a phrenſie, or deſperate obſtinacy. <hi>Antoninus</hi> the Roman Emperour, in his <hi>Meditations;</hi> and <hi>Epictetus</hi> (the ſame of whom we have ſpoken before) in his <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> ſet out by <hi>Arrianus,</hi> take notice of it with ſome admiration. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logetick, &amp; in his Treatiſe <hi>De ſpectaculis,</hi> treats of it large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>Sulpitius Severus</hi> ſpeaking of thoſe times, ſaith that <hi>tunc Martyria, &amp;c. ſuffering of martyrdom was then ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with as much earneſtnes, as Biſhopricks were</hi> (he lived about 400. yeers after Chriſt) <hi>in his days.</hi> That he ſpake it not hyperbolically, may appear (were there no other proofs) by thoſe many laws and conſtitutions of the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt wilfull martyrdome, or ſuch as offered themſelves to death for their faith, which by men, women, and even children, of all ranks and qualities, was frequently done in thoſe times. And by this contempt of death and of the world, as much and more then by miracles or any thing elſe, did Chriſtians conquer the world, and in deſpite of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:113795:49"/> all oppoſition, (as great as can be imagined) ſubdued it to the Chriſtian faith. Such was the faith of thoſe times.</p>
               <p>If the ſame effects of Chriſt his example have not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in all ages, it is not becauſe the example it ſelf hath leſs efficacy then it had then, but becauſe Chriſt is not apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the ſame faith, as he was then. Chriſt himſelf did foretell of the little faith of the latter times. It is not all, to be called a Chriſtian. The Apoſtle denyed them (we know) to be true Jews, all, which were Jews outwardly; or to be the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> all, that were of the ſeed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> but had not his faith.</p>
               <p>What the violence of ſome preſent ſufferings, (be they ſufferings of the body, or ſufferings of the mind) or the violent apprehenſion of future, in either kind, may do for a while; how far it may prevail upon ſome, ſound and ſolid otherwiſe; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if the temper of a naturally ſoft or paſſionate diſpoſition doth concur, I ſhall not here enquire. Though grace and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture goe not always by the ſame principles, yet there may be, where true grace is, ſo much of nature remaining ſomtimes, as to verifie that of <hi>Ariſtotles,</hi> (that incomparable Naturaliſt) that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>thoſe that are in any paſsion, can not judge of the truth.</hi> But if any profeſſed Chriſtian in his more ſober, retired, and free thoughts can ſettle himſelf to ſuch an opinion as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to wonder at the miſeries and calamities of others, (good and godly men) or to bemoan himſelf in the ſame caſe as mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable indeed and hardly dealt with; that man by ſuch an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion doth renounce the faith he profeſſeth, and what ſhew ſoever he make to the world, yet cannot but be conſcious to himſelf of his own infidelity.</p>
               <p>All Chriſtians are not <hi>Pauls,</hi> I grant; though his zeal to God, and his charity to men,<note place="margin">Act. 26.29</note> did once prompt him to ſuch a wiſh. God forbid, heaven ſhould be opened to none but ſuch. As of glory, ſo of faith, of zeal, though true and ſyncere, and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:113795:50"/> perfect in its kind, there may be many degrees. We are allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if we may be free, rather to be free; if rich and honourable in the world, by good and lawfull means, rather to be ſo, then poor and contemptible. That common ſoldier is not commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, who to ſhew his valour, runs into dangers, wilfully; or ſets upon the enemy without a command. In this our Chriſtian warfare ſome are Captains and Generals, that muſt leade and command: the greateſt part, are common ſoldiers, who if they readily follow, &amp; execute, when called, it is as much as needs. S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf could ſay, <hi>I know how to be abaſed; and I know how to abound.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4.12.</note> If there be a firm reſolution, and anſwerable due preparation, if God ſhall call us to it, to ſay with S. <hi>Paul, I account all things but dung, &amp;c.</hi> ſuch a reſolution, and ſuch a preparation may in the eyes of God (who as he onely can ſee, ſo moſt obſerves the heart) ſtand for the deed it ſelf.</p>
               <p>And ſo may thoſe generall expreſſions, as, <hi>Whoſoever doth not bear his croſſe, &amp;c.</hi> and, <hi>Whoſoever will live godlily, &amp;c.</hi> and that <hi>through many tribulations, &amp;c.</hi> and the like, be qualified and underſtood: of the reſolution &amp; preparation, (if true and reall) as well as of the deed and event it ſelf. And certainly ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious men, who actually and perſonally never taſted, either not at all, (if ſuch may be found) or very little, of the troubles and miſeries of this life, by this kind of preparation, as alſo by their fellow-feeling (as in hearty compaſſion, ſo in readineſſe to aſſiſt and relieve to their power) in the ſufferings of others, might be as great ſufferers before God, as ſome others, who ſuffer much more, but happily not ſo patiently, nor with ſo much reflexion upon others, as they ſhould. But where nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther actuall patient enduring, nor this hearty preparation is found, there we may certainly from this doctrine of Chriſt his <hi>Exinanition</hi> conclude, that there is no reall communion with Chriſt, nor true ſenſe of Chriſtianity.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113795:50"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
